<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="urn:ietf:rfc:7991" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
     docName="draft-drake-email-hardware-attestation-00"
     ipr="trust200902"
     submissionType="IETF"
     category="std"
     consensus="true"
     xml:lang="en"
     version="3">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="Hardware Email Attestation">
      Hardware Attestation for Email Sender Verification
    </title>

    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft"
                value="draft-drake-email-hardware-attestation-00"/>

    <author fullname="Christopher Drake" initials="C." surname="Drake">
      <organization>1id.com</organization>
      <address>
        <email>cnd@1id.com</email>
        <uri>https://1id.com</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2026" month="March" day="19"/>

    <area>Security</area>
    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>

    <keyword>hardware attestation</keyword>
    <keyword>email</keyword>
    <keyword>TPM</keyword>
    <keyword>PIV</keyword>
    <keyword>Sybil</keyword>
    <keyword>spam</keyword>
    <keyword>agent identity</keyword>
    <keyword>AI agents</keyword>
    <keyword>URN</keyword>
    <keyword>reputation</keyword>
    <keyword>transport-independent</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>
        This document defines a mechanism for automated email senders
        (AI agents, bots, and autonomous systems) to include hardware
        attestation evidence in message headers, enabling receiving
        mail servers to cryptographically verify that an email was
        composed on a device containing a genuine hardware security
        component -- such as a Trusted Platform Module (TPM), a PIV
        smart card (e.g., YubiKey), a virtual TPM, or a
        software-managed key -- from a known manufacturer or issuer.
        The verification chain runs from the email header to a
        manufacturer's root Certificate Authority (for hardware-backed
        attestation) or to an issuer's verification key (for
        issuer-certified attestation), requiring no trust in any single
        intermediary identity service.
      </t>
      <t>
        Each automated sender is assigned a persistent agent identity,
        expressed as a URN in the "aid" (Agent Identity) namespace
        (<xref target="RFC8141"/>), enabling federated issuance by
        multiple independent identity providers and persistent
        reputation tracking across protocols and platforms.
      </t>
      <t>
        As a companion mechanism, this document defines a
        privacy-preserving alternative using SD-JWT (Selective
        Disclosure JWT, <xref target="RFC9901"/>) where the sender can
        prove specific claims about their hardware trust level without
        revealing their hardware identity.
      </t>
      <t>
        Together, these mechanisms provide both Sybil-resistant
        authentication and a foundation for reputation building: each
        identity requires a unique hardware security component, making
        large-scale automated abuse economically infeasible regardless
        of advances in artificial intelligence, while the persistent
        hardware-anchored identity enables receiving systems to
        accumulate trust signals over time.  Software-only agents MAY
        participate at a lower trust tier, building reputation from an
        initial baseline rather than from a hardware-anchored starting
        point.
      </t>
      <t>
        While this document specifies these mechanisms for email message
        headers, the attestation formats defined herein -- both the CMS
        attestation bundle and the SD-JWT trust proof -- are
        self-contained, transport-independent data structures applicable
        to HTTP headers, agent-to-agent messaging, payment
        authorisation, and other Internet protocols.
      </t>
    </abstract>

  </front>

  <middle>

    <!-- ====================================================== -->
    <section anchor="introduction">
      <name>Introduction</name>

      <t>
        Email authentication today relies on three complementary
        mechanisms: SPF <xref target="RFC7208"/> verifies that the
        transmitting mail server's IP address is authorised for the
        domain, DKIM <xref target="RFC6376"/> provides a domain-level
        cryptographic signature, and DMARC <xref target="RFC7489"/>
        ties them together with policy.  These mechanisms prove that an
        email was authorised by a domain.  They do not prove anything
        about the agent or device that composed the message.
      </t>
      <t>
        This distinction has become critical.  The rapid proliferation
        of autonomous AI agents capable of composing human-quality text
        has rendered content-based spam detection increasingly
        ineffective.  An attacker can register unlimited domains,
        configure valid SPF/DKIM/DMARC, and use AI to generate
        messages indistinguishable from legitimate correspondence.
        Every existing defence -- CAPTCHAs, phone verification,
        behavioural analysis, IP reputation -- fails when the attacker
        is an AI that can operate at scale with near-zero marginal cost.
      </t>
      <t>
        The fundamental problem is that all existing sender identity
        signals are software-based and therefore copyable at zero cost.
        This document proposes anchoring sender identity to hardware,
        applying the remote attestation architecture of
        <xref target="RFC9334"/> to email: specifically, to the
        tamper-resistant hardware security components present in
        virtually every modern computing device.
      </t>
      <t>
        A hardware security component -- whether a discrete TPM chip, a
        firmware TPM (e.g., Intel PTT or AMD fTPM), a PIV smart card
        (e.g., YubiKey), or a virtual TPM provided by a hypervisor --
        contains a unique identity key burned in or generated at
        manufacturing time, with a certificate chaining to the
        manufacturer's root CA.  This key cannot be extracted, cloned,
        or transferred.  By signing email content with a
        hardware-resident key and including or linking the certificate chain in the
        message headers, an automated sender proves that the email
        originated on a specific, genuine piece of hardware.
      </t>
      <t>
        Receiving mail servers can verify this proof by validating the
        certificate chain against manufacturer root CAs -- the same CAs
        they already trust for Secure Boot, platform integrity, and
        hardware-dependent operations.  No new trust relationships are
        required.
      </t>
      <t>
        This document defines two complementary mechanisms:
      </t>
      <ol>
        <li>
          <strong>Direct Hardware Attestation</strong>
          (<xref target="direct-attestation"/>): A CMS
          <xref target="RFC5652"/> signed-data structure containing the
          attestation signature and full certificate chain, carried in
          or linked from an email header.  Verifiable directly against manufacturer
          root CAs.  Optimised for deliverability and reputation
          tracking.
        </li>
        <li>
          <strong>SD-JWT Trust Proof</strong>
          (<xref target="sd-jwt-proof"/>): A Selective Disclosure JWT
          <xref target="RFC9901"/> issued by an identity provider
          (issuer), where the sender selects which claims to reveal.
          Optimised for privacy in contexts where revealing hardware
          identity is undesirable.
        </li>
      </ol>
      <section anchor="design-principles">
        <name>Design Principles</name>
        <t>
          The following principles guide the design of this
          specification and are referenced throughout the document:
        </t>
        <dl>
          <dt>Automated-Sender Focus</dt>
          <dd>This specification targets AI agents, bots, and
          autonomous systems.  It is not intended for individual human
          users (see <xref target="applicability"/>).  The privacy
          trade-offs are acceptable for automated senders but
          disproportionate for human correspondence.</dd>

          <dt>Transport Independence</dt>
          <dd>The attestation formats defined herein -- the CMS
          attestation bundle and the SD-JWT trust proof -- are
          self-contained data structures that can be carried in any
          protocol capable of transporting octet strings.  This
          document specifies the email transport binding;
          <xref target="other-transports"/> discusses applicability
          to HTTP and other protocols.</dd>

          <dt>Federated Issuance</dt>
          <dd>Any organisation that owns a DNS domain can operate as an
          Issuer.  No central authority or coordination is required
          beyond DNS ownership.  This mirrors the federated model of
          email itself (see <xref target="issuer-discovery"/>).</dd>

          <dt>Inclusive Trust Tiers</dt>
          <dd>Agents with genuine hardware security components receive
          the highest trust, but agents with virtual hardware or
          software-only keys can still participate at lower trust
          tiers, building reputation over time.  This inclusivity
          avoids an all-or-nothing barrier to adoption.</dd>

          <dt>Reputation as the Goal</dt>
          <dd>Sybil resistance is a means, not an end.  The
          persistent, hardware-anchored identities defined here exist
          to enable receiving systems to build and query reputation
          over time, rewarding good behaviour and flagging bad.</dd>
        </dl>
      </section>

      <section anchor="requirements-language">
        <name>Requirements Language</name>
        <t>
          The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
          "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED",
          "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document
          are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14
          <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when,
          and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="terminology">
        <name>Terminology</name>
        <dl>
          <dt>Hardware Attestation Mechanism</dt>
          <dd>A tamper-resistant hardware or firmware component capable
          of protecting private keys and producing cryptographic
          attestation statements verifiable to a manufacturer or
          platform Certificate Authority.  Examples include TPM 2.0
          devices (discrete and firmware), PIV tokens (e.g., YubiKey),
          and virtual TPMs.  This document also accommodates
          software-managed keys at a lower trust tier for agents that
          lack hardware security components but wish to participate in
          the reputation ecosystem.</dd>

          <dt>TPM</dt>
          <dd>Trusted Platform Module, as specified by the Trusted
          Computing Group (TCG) <xref target="TCG-TPM2"/>.
          This document assumes TPM 2.0.  A TPM may be a discrete
          chip, a firmware implementation (Intel PTT, AMD fTPM), or a
          virtual instance provided by a hypervisor.</dd>

          <dt>EK</dt>
          <dd>Endorsement Key.  A unique RSA or ECC key pair generated
          inside the TPM at manufacturing time, as profiled in
          <xref target="TCG-EK-PROFILE"/>.  The EK private key
          never leaves the TPM.  The EK certificate is signed by the
          chip manufacturer's CA and serves as the persistent hardware
          identity for the device.</dd>

          <dt>AK</dt>
          <dd>Attestation Key.  A signing key created inside a hardware
          security component, certified against the device's identity
          key (EK for TPM, attestation certificate for PIV) to prove it
          resides in the same device.  In this specification, the AK
          SHOULD be created as a transient object and SHOULD NOT be
          persisted in non-volatile storage, to avoid consuming limited
          hardware resources.  See
          <xref target="transient-key-model"/>.</dd>

          <dt>Identity Certificate</dt>
          <dd>The manufacturer-issued certificate that identifies a
          specific hardware security component.  For TPMs, this is the
          EK certificate.  For PIV tokens, this is the device
          attestation certificate.  The SHA-256 hash of the
          SubjectPublicKeyInfo DER encoding from this certificate
          serves as the hardware fingerprint.  The fingerprint is
          derived from the public key structure rather than the
          certificate as a whole, so that the fingerprint remains
          stable if the manufacturer reissues the certificate (e.g.,
          to extend validity or update metadata) without changing the
          underlying key pair.</dd>

          <dt>Manufacturer CA</dt>
          <dd>The Certificate Authority operated by the hardware
          manufacturer (e.g., Intel, AMD, Infineon, Yubico) that signs
          identity certificates.  Root CA certificates are publicly
          available.</dd>

          <dt>Agent Identity</dt>
          <dd>A persistent, globally unique identifier for an
          autonomous agent, expressed as a URN in the "aid" namespace
          (<xref target="agent-identity-format"/>).  Agent identities
          are assigned by issuers and are bound to specific hardware
          via the issuer's anti-Sybil registry.</dd>

          <dt>Issuer</dt>
          <dd>An entity that verifies hardware attestation evidence,
          maintains an anti-Sybil registry (ensuring one hardware
          device maps to at most one identity), and issues trust
          assertions (e.g., SD-JWTs) about enrolled agents.  An
          Issuer is OPTIONAL for Mode 1 (Direct Hardware Attestation)
          and REQUIRED for Mode 2 (SD-JWT Trust Proof).  See
          <xref target="issuer-discovery"/> for discovery and the
          federated issuance model.</dd>

          <dt>Trust Tier</dt>
          <dd>A classification of an agent's hardware trust level,
          assigned by an Issuer.  Defined tiers include "sovereign"
          (genuine non-virtual hardware TPM or discrete security
          chip), "portable" (PIV smart card such as YubiKey),
          "virtual" (hypervisor-provided virtual TPM), and "declared"
          (software-only key, no hardware attestation).  Verifiers use
          trust tiers to apply differentiated policy.  For identities
          with multiple enrolled devices of different types, Issuers
          that support multi-device identities MAY report the trust
          tier of the device used for the most recent attestation
          rather than a static assignment.  Verifiers SHOULD therefore
          expect the same agent identity URN to appear with different
          trust tier values over time.</dd>

          <dt>Sybil Attack</dt>
          <dd>An attack where a single adversary creates many
          pseudonymous identities to subvert a reputation or
          trust system.</dd>
        </dl>
      </section>
    </section>

    <!-- ====================================================== -->
    <section anchor="problem-statement">
      <name>Problem Statement</name>

      <t>
        The economic model of email spam has historically depended on
        the near-zero cost of sending messages.  Anti-spam defences
        have worked by raising costs (CAPTCHAs impose human attention
        costs, IP reputation requires infrastructure investment,
        phone verification requires SIM procurement).
      </t>
      <t>
        AI agents eliminate these costs.  An AI can solve CAPTCHAs,
        generate unique content for each message, rotate through
        residential proxy IPs, and operate continuously without human
        attention.  The result is that cost-based anti-spam defences
        approach zero effectiveness as AI capabilities improve.
      </t>
      <t>
        Hardware attestation re-introduces a cost floor that AI
        cannot eliminate: each sender identity requires a physical
        security component.  These components have real manufacturing
        costs, exist in physical supply chains, and each contains a
        globally unique key pair certified by the manufacturer.  An
        attacker seeking to create N sender identities needs N
        physical devices, each with genuine hardware -- a cost of
        approximately $20-2000 per identity compared to approximately
        $0 per identity with software-only approaches.
      </t>
      <t>
        Furthermore, because each hardware identity is unique and
        persistent, receiving mail servers can build per-hardware
        reputation.  A device that sends spam is flagged permanently.
        The attacker cannot simply create a new account -- they need
        new physical hardware.
      </t>
      <t>
        This specification also accommodates software-only agents at a
        lower trust tier.  An agent that manages its own key pair
        without hardware protection can still participate in the
        reputation ecosystem, building trust over time from a lower
        starting point.  This inclusivity recognises that not all
        legitimate agents have access to hardware security components,
        while maintaining clear differentiation between
        hardware-backed and software-only trust levels.
      </t>
    </section>

    <!-- ====================================================== -->
    <section anchor="applicability">
      <name>Applicability</name>
      <t>
        This specification targets authentication of automated
        senders -- AI agents, bots, and high-volume automated
        systems -- where Sybil resistance justifies hardware-anchored
        identity.  The proliferation of autonomous AI agents capable
        of generating human-quality content at scale is the primary
        motivation.
      </t>
      <t>
        This specification is NOT intended or recommended for
        individual human users sending personal or low-volume email.
        Human senders using consumer mail user agents (e.g., Gmail
        web client, Outlook) face privacy risks from Mode 1 Direct
        Attestation that are disproportionate to the benefit: the
        hardware fingerprint uniquely identifies the sending device
        across all messages and contexts, enabling long-term tracking
        that exceeds current email privacy norms.  Mode 2 (SD-JWT
        Trust Proof) mitigates this via selective disclosure but
        requires enrollment with an Issuer, which is not a typical
        consumer workflow.
      </t>
      <t>
        Mail User Agents (MUAs) designed for interactive human use
        MUST NOT enable Direct Hardware Attestation (Mode 1) by
        default.  Activation MUST require explicit, per-device user
        consent that warns of persistent cross-context tracking
        before any attestation header is added to outgoing messages.
        Operators of human-facing email services MAY offer hardware
        attestation as an opt-in feature (e.g., via a browser
        extension or MUA plugin), but MUST provide clear disclosure
        of the linkability implications before activation.
        Receivers SHOULD NOT penalise the absence of hardware
        attestation from senders exhibiting human-characteristic
        patterns (e.g., low volume, natural language variance,
        interactive reply chains).
      </t>
      <t>
        For human identity proofs in email, existing mechanisms
        such as S/MIME <xref target="RFC8551"/> and DANE
        <xref target="RFC7671"/> remain appropriate.
      </t>
      <t>
        The attestation formats are transport-independent by design
        (see <xref target="design-principles"/>); this document
        specifies the email transport binding as the primary
        application.
      </t>
    </section>

    <!-- ====================================================== -->
    <section anchor="architecture">
      <name>Architecture</name>

      <t>
        This section defines the identity model, hardware mechanism
        taxonomy, key lifecycle, and issuer discovery procedures that
        underpin both attestation modes.
      </t>

      <section anchor="agent-identity-format">
        <name>Agent Identity Format</name>
        <t>
          Agent identities in this specification use the URN format
          defined in <xref target="RFC8141"/> with the "aid" (Agent
          Identity) namespace identifier.
        </t>

        <artwork type="abnf"><![CDATA[
aid-urn          = "urn:aid:" issuer-namespace ":" agent-id

issuer-namespace = dns-label *("." dns-label)
dns-label        = let-dig *(let-dig-hyp) let-dig / let-dig
let-dig          = ALPHA / DIGIT
let-dig-hyp      = ALPHA / DIGIT / "-"

agent-id         = dns-label
        ]]></artwork>

        <t>
          The issuer-namespace uses reverse DNS notation to identify
          the organisation that enrolled the agent and verified its
          hardware.  The agent-id is assigned by the Issuer and MUST
          be unique within that Issuer's namespace.
        </t>
        <t>
          The agent-id MUST conform to DNS label syntax
          (<xref target="RFC1035"/> Section 2.3.1): lowercase ASCII
          letters, digits, and hyphens, not beginning or ending with a
          hyphen, maximum 63 octets.  Internationalised agent
          identifiers MUST use the "xn--" ACE prefix encoding defined
          in <xref target="RFC5891"/>.  Underscores MUST NOT appear
          in the agent-id.
        </t>
        <t>
          Examples:
        </t>
        <ul>
          <li><tt>urn:aid:com.1id:1id-ty62muvf</tt></li>
          <li><tt>urn:aid:com.anthropic:claude-prod-7x9k</tt></li>
          <li><tt>urn:aid:io.openai:gpt4-instance-42</tt></li>
        </ul>
        <t>
          URN equivalence follows <xref target="RFC8141"/>
          Section 3: the "urn" scheme and "aid" NID are
          case-insensitive; the issuer-namespace and agent-id are
          case-sensitive (and MUST be lowercase).
        </t>
        <t>
          Agent identities are persistent by design: an Issuer MUST
          NOT reassign an agent-id to a different entity, even after
          the original identity is revoked or expired.  This
          persistence is essential for reputation systems that
          accumulate trust signals over the lifetime of an identity.
          See <xref target="identity-hardware-cardinality"/> for the
          rules governing the relationship between agent identities
          and hardware devices.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="identity-hardware-cardinality">
        <name>Identity-to-Hardware Cardinality</name>
        <t>
          The agent identity URN (aid) is the primary, stable
          identifier for reputation tracking.  The hardware
          fingerprint is an implementation detail that anchors the
          identity to physical hardware.  The relationship between
          these two identifiers is governed by the following rules:
        </t>
        <dl>
          <dt>Many hardware devices MAY back one agent identity</dt>
          <dd><t>An Issuer MAY bind additional hardware devices to an
          existing agent identity over time, to support legitimate
          hardware migration (e.g., retiring old servers, replacing
          failed TPMs), secure backup and recovery (e.g., a YubiKey
          stored in a safe), or adding capacity for a high-volume
          sending agent.  This does not amplify reputation: a single
          agent identity has a single reputation regardless of how
          many devices back it.  If the identity is flagged for
          abuse, all devices associated with it are equally
          affected.  The Issuer SHOULD require the agent to prove
          control of the existing identity (e.g., by signing with
          the previously enrolled hardware) before accepting a new
          device.  Verifiers that track both the aid and the
          hardware fingerprint SHOULD expect that a given aid may
          appear with different hardware fingerprints over its
          lifetime.</t>
          <t>Each device bound to an agent identity is permanently
          associated with that identity.  An Issuer MAY disable a
          device (preventing it from producing valid attestations)
          but MUST NOT remove the device-to-identity binding.  A
          disabled device remains counted against the identity and
          MUST NOT be re-enrolled under any other agent-id, even
          after disablement.  This permanence prevents reputation
          laundering via device recycling.</t>
          <t>An Issuer MUST enforce trust tier compatibility when
          binding additional devices: all hardware devices backing a
          single agent identity MUST be of comparable trust tier.
          Specifically, sovereign-tier hardware (typ=TPM) and
          portable-tier hardware (typ=PIV) are compatible and MAY
          back the same identity.  Virtual-tier hardware (typ=VRT)
          MAY back the same identity as other virtual-tier devices
          but MUST NOT be mixed with sovereign or portable
          hardware.  Declared-tier keys (typ=SFT) MUST NOT be bound
          to an identity that has any hardware-backed device.  This
          constraint prevents an identity from simultaneously
          claiming hardware-anchored trust and relying on
          unprotected software keys.</t>
          <t>When an identity has multiple devices of compatible but
          different types (e.g., one sovereign TPM and one portable
          PIV), the trust_tier disclosed in attestation tokens
          (Mode 2) or the typ parameter in attestation headers
          (Mode 1) reflects the specific device used for that
          attestation, not a static property of the identity.
          Verifiers SHOULD therefore expect the same agent identity
          URN to appear with different trust tier values across
          different messages.</t></dd>

          <dt>One hardware device MUST NOT back multiple agent
          identities from the same Issuer</dt>
          <dd>An Issuer MUST NOT enroll the same hardware device
          (identified by its identity certificate public key hash)
          under more than one agent-id within that Issuer's
          namespace.  This is the fundamental anti-Sybil invariant:
          it ensures that creating N agent identities requires N
          distinct hardware devices.  Issuers MUST maintain a
          registry mapping identity certificate public key hashes to
          agent-ids and MUST reject enrollment attempts that would
          violate this constraint.  This binding is permanent: once a
          hardware device has been bound to an agent identity, it
          MUST NOT be reassigned to a different agent identity, even
          if it is later disabled or removed from the original
          identity.  An Issuer MAY disable a hardware device
          (preventing it from being used for attestation) but MUST
          NOT permit that device to be enrolled under any other
          agent-id.  This prevents reputation laundering attacks where
          a flagged device is removed from a bad-reputation identity
          and enrolled under a fresh identity.</dd>

          <dt>Cross-Issuer binding is permitted</dt>
          <dd>A single hardware device MAY be enrolled with multiple
          independent Issuers, each assigning its own agent-id.
          This is by design: Issuers are independent authorities, and
          the anti-Sybil invariant is scoped to a single Issuer's
          namespace.  Cross-Issuer duplication is trivially
          detectable by any verifier that tracks hardware
          fingerprints: the same fingerprint appearing under
          multiple agent identities from different Issuers reveals
          the shared hardware.  Verifiers MAY apply policy based on
          this signal (e.g., treating the device as lower trust if
          it maintains identities with many Issuers
          simultaneously).</dd>
        </dl>
        <t>
          Because the agent identity is the stable reputation anchor,
          verifiers SHOULD use the aid URN as the primary key for
          reputation systems.  The hardware fingerprint serves as a
          secondary signal: it provides Sybil resistance at the
          hardware layer and enables reputation tracking for agents
          that do not present an aid.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="hw-mechanisms">
        <name>Hardware Attestation Mechanisms</name>
        <t>
          This specification supports multiple hardware security
          technologies through a common abstraction.  Each mechanism
          provides an identity certificate (signed by the manufacturer)
          and a signing capability (used for per-message attestation).
          The hardware type is declared in the attestation header via
          the "typ" parameter.
        </t>
        <table>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>typ value</th>
              <th>Technology</th>
              <th>Identity Certificate</th>
              <th>Trust Tier</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td>TPM</td>
              <td>TPM 2.0 (discrete or firmware)</td>
              <td>EK Certificate</td>
              <td>sovereign</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>PIV</td>
              <td>PIV smart card (e.g., YubiKey)</td>
              <td>Device Attestation Certificate</td>
              <td>portable</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>VRT</td>
              <td>Virtual TPM (hypervisor-provided)</td>
              <td>vTPM EK Certificate</td>
              <td>virtual</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>SFT</td>
              <td>Software-managed key</td>
              <td>Issuer-signed certificate</td>
              <td>declared</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
        <t>
          Additional hardware types MAY be defined in future
          specifications by registering new "typ" values with IANA
          (see <xref target="iana-considerations"/>).
        </t>
        <t>
          For TPM-based attestation (typ=TPM), the identity
          certificate is the Endorsement Key (EK) certificate,
          provisioned at manufacturing time and stored in the TPM's
          non-volatile memory.  The EK certificate chains to the TPM
          manufacturer's root CA (e.g., Intel, AMD, Infineon).
        </t>
        <t>
          For PIV-based attestation (typ=PIV), the identity
          certificate is the device attestation certificate issued by
          the token manufacturer (e.g., Yubico).  The signing key is
          a PIV authentication key resident on the token.
        </t>
        <t>
          For virtual TPM attestation (typ=VRT), the identity
          certificate is the vTPM's EK certificate, signed by the
          hypervisor vendor's CA (e.g., VMware, Microsoft).  Verifiers
          MUST distinguish virtual from physical hardware; see
          <xref target="sybil-vtpm"/> for Sybil resistance
          implications.
        </t>
        <t>
          For software-only attestation (typ=SFT), the signing key is
          a software-managed key pair with no hardware protection.
          The identity certificate is issued by the Issuer at
          enrollment time.  Software-only attestation provides no
          hardware-based Sybil resistance but allows agents to
          participate in the reputation ecosystem at a lower trust
          tier.  A legitimate agent that protects its key and
          builds reputation over time can achieve meaningful trust
          even without hardware backing.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="transient-key-model">
        <name>Transient Key Model</name>
        <t>
          For TPM-based attestation, this specification RECOMMENDS a
          transient key model in which the Attestation Key (AK) is
          created as a transient TPM object (via TPM2_CreatePrimary)
          and is NOT persisted in the TPM's non-volatile (NV) storage.
          This avoids consuming limited NV slots, which are a scarce
          resource on most TPMs (typically 3-7 loaded objects at once).
        </t>
        <t>
          The transient key lifecycle is:
        </t>
        <ol>
          <li>
            <strong>Read EK certificate</strong> from the TPM's NV
            storage (index 0x01C00002 for RSA EK).  This is a
            read-only operation.  The EK certificate MAY be cached
            indefinitely as it does not change.
          </li>
          <li>
            <strong>Create transient AK</strong> via
            TPM2_CreatePrimary under the endorsement hierarchy with a
            fixed template.  Because the template and the Endorsement
            Primary Seed (EPS) are constant, this deterministically
            produces the same key on every invocation.
          </li>
          <li>
            <strong>Binding verification</strong> (one-time, during
            enrollment with an Issuer): The Issuer creates a
            credential challenge (TPM2_MakeCredential) encrypted to
            the EK; the agent decrypts it (TPM2_ActivateCredential),
            proving the AK resides in the same TPM as the EK.  The
            resulting AK certificate is stored client-side (outside the
            TPM) and reused across signing operations.
          </li>
          <li>
            <strong>Sign</strong> the attestation content with the
            transient AK (TPM2_Sign).
          </li>
          <li>
            <strong>Flush</strong> the transient AK handle
            (TPM2_FlushContext) to free the object slot.
          </li>
        </ol>
        <t>
          Implementations SHOULD flush transient objects immediately
          after use.  If TPM2_CreatePrimary returns
          TPM_RC_OBJECT_MEMORY (0x0902), the implementation MUST flush
          existing transient handles and retry.
        </t>
        <t>
          The EK certificate is the persistent hardware identifier.
          The AK is ephemeral infrastructure -- it exists only long
          enough to produce a signature, then is discarded.  No data
          is written to the TPM's non-volatile memory at any point in
          this protocol.
        </t>
        <t>
          The transient AK is deterministic within a given Endorsement
          Primary Seed (EPS) epoch.  The EPS is re-randomised when the
          TPM is cleared (TPM2_Clear) or reset to factory defaults.
          After such an event, the AK public key changes and the agent
          MUST re-enroll with its Issuer to establish a new AK-to-EK
          binding.  The EK certificate remains constant across TPM
          clears, so the hardware identity persists even though the AK
          changes.
        </t>
        <t>
          Note: On some platform configurations (particularly Windows
          with default TPM Base Services policy), reading the EK
          certificate from NV storage may require a one-time operating
          system configuration change or elevated access during initial
          enrollment.  Once the EK certificate has been read and cached
          client-side, subsequent attestation operations do not require
          elevation.  Implementations that cannot read the EK
          certificate directly MAY derive the EK public key via
          TPM2_CreatePrimary with the TCG EK template and use the
          resulting public key hash as the hardware fingerprint;
          verifiers can then query manufacturer APIs (e.g., Intel
          Trusted Services) to obtain the full certificate if needed
          for chain validation.  Alternatively, the Issuer can perform
          EK certificate extraction during enrollment and include it in
          the AK certificate it issues.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="issuer-discovery">
        <name>Issuer Discovery</name>
        <t>
          When a verifier encounters an agent identity URN, it extracts
          the Issuer's domain from the issuer-namespace by reversing
          the dot-separated labels.
        </t>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
Example:
  URN: urn:aid:com.1id:1id-ty62muvf
  issuer-namespace: com.1id
  Issuer domain: 1id.com
        ]]></artwork>
        <t>
          The verifier discovers the Issuer's signing key and
          endpoints through the mechanisms described below.  The
          DNS-based method is RECOMMENDED for email because it
          piggybacks on infrastructure that mail servers already
          query for DKIM, SPF, and DMARC, requires no outbound
          HTTPS connections during verification, and inherits the
          same domain-ownership guarantees that protect existing
          email authentication.  Any organisation that owns a DNS
          domain can operate as an Issuer by implementing the
          enrollment protocol, publishing a signing key (via DNS
          and/or JWKS), and maintaining an anti-Sybil registry.
          No central registration or coordination is required
          beyond DNS ownership.
        </t>

        <section anchor="issuer-key-dns">
          <name>DNS-Published Issuer Key</name>
          <t>
            Issuers SHOULD publish their SD-JWT signing key as a DNS
            TXT record at the well-known name
            <tt>_hwattest.{domain}</tt>, following the same
            pattern as DKIM key records
            (<xref target="RFC6376"/> Section 3.6).
          </t>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
Example DNS TXT record:

  _hwattest.1id.com.  IN TXT (
    "v=hwattest1; alg=ES256; "
    "p=MFkwEwYHKoZIzj0CAQYIKoZIzj0DAQcDQgAE..."
  )
          ]]></artwork>
          <t>
            The TXT record value uses a tag=value format with
            semicolon separators:
          </t>
          <dl>
            <dt>v</dt>
            <dd>REQUIRED.  Version.  MUST be "hwattest1".</dd>

            <dt>alg</dt>
            <dd>REQUIRED.  The JWS algorithm used by the Issuer
            to sign SD-JWTs (e.g., "ES256", "PS256").</dd>

            <dt>p</dt>
            <dd>REQUIRED.  The Issuer's public key, base64-encoded.
            For EC keys, this is the SubjectPublicKeyInfo DER
            encoding.  For RSA keys, this is the PKCS#1 DER
            encoding.  The format matches the DKIM p= tag
            (<xref target="RFC6376"/> Section 3.6.1).</dd>

            <dt>kid</dt>
            <dd>OPTIONAL.  Key identifier matching the kid in the
            SD-JWT header.  When present, verifiers use this to
            select the correct key if the Issuer rotates keys.</dd>

            <dt>t</dt>
            <dd>OPTIONAL.  Key type: "active" (default) or
            "revoked".  When set to "revoked", verifiers MUST
            reject SD-JWTs signed with this key.  This allows
            Issuers to revoke a compromised key via a DNS update
            without waiting for TTL expiry of cached JWKS
            responses.</dd>
          </dl>
          <t>
            Verifiers MUST query this DNS record before falling
            back to HTTPS-based discovery.  The DNS TTL controls
            caching; Issuers SHOULD set a TTL between 3600 and
            86400 seconds (1 to 24 hours).  For key rotation, the
            Issuer publishes the new key in DNS, waits for the old
            TTL to expire, then marks the old key as revoked.
          </t>
          <t>
            This approach provides several security advantages for
            email verification:
          </t>
          <ul>
            <li>No outbound HTTPS connections during mail
            processing, eliminating DDoS amplification and SSRF
            risks that external URI fetches would introduce.</li>
            <li>Domain ownership is proven by DNS control, the
            same trust anchor used by DKIM and SPF.  A forged
            Hardware-Trust-Proof header claiming an Issuer domain
            the attacker does not control will fail verification
            because the attacker cannot publish a matching DNS
            key record.</li>
            <li>DNS infrastructure is already hardened against
            abuse by mail operators (rate limiting, caching,
            DNSSEC).</li>
            <li>Key revocation propagates through DNS TTL expiry,
            providing a well-understood and operationally familiar
            mechanism.</li>
          </ul>
        </section>

        <section anchor="issuer-https-discovery">
          <name>HTTPS-Based Discovery (Fallback)</name>
          <t>
            When no DNS TXT record is found at
            <tt>_hwattest.{domain}</tt>, or when the verifier
            operates in a non-email context (e.g., HTTP API
            verification), the verifier MAY discover the Issuer's
            key via HTTPS:
          </t>
          <dl>
            <dt>OIDC Discovery</dt>
            <dd><tt>https://{domain}/.well-known/openid-configuration</tt>
            - Standard OpenID Connect discovery document containing
            the JWKS URI for SD-JWT signature verification.</dd>

            <dt>Issuer Metadata (OPTIONAL)</dt>
            <dd><tt>https://{domain}/.well-known/aid-issuer.json</tt>
            - JSON document describing the Issuer's capabilities,
            supported trust tiers, enrollment endpoint, and
            anti-Sybil policy.</dd>

            <dt>Manufacturer CA Trust Store (OPTIONAL)</dt>
            <dd><tt>https://{domain}/.well-known/hw-manufacturer-cas.pem</tt>
            - PEM-encoded bundle of hardware manufacturer root CA
            certificates that this Issuer accepts during enrollment.
            Verifiers performing Mode 1 verification SHOULD maintain
            their own trust store rather than relying on this
            endpoint.</dd>
          </dl>
          <t>
            Verifiers using HTTPS-based discovery SHOULD cache the
            JWKS with a TTL of at least 1 hour and at most 24 hours.
            Verifiers MUST NOT follow redirects to domains other
            than the Issuer's domain, to prevent open-redirect
            attacks.
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <!-- ====================================================== -->
    <section anchor="direct-attestation">
      <name>Mode 1: Direct Hardware Attestation</name>

      <t>
        This section defines a CMS-based attestation bundle containing
        a hardware-anchored signature and its full certificate chain,
        presented here as an email header field.  The CMS structure
        is transport-independent (see
        <xref target="design-principles"/>).
      </t>

      <section anchor="attestation-chain">
        <name>Attestation Evidence Structure</name>
        <t>
          The attestation evidence consists of the following
          certificates, ordered from leaf to root:
        </t>
        <ol>
          <li>
            <strong>AK Certificate:</strong> Issued by an Issuer after
            successful completion of the binding verification protocol
            (e.g., TPM2_MakeCredential / TPM2_ActivateCredential for
            TPMs, or manufacturer attestation verification for PIV
            tokens).  Binds the AK public key to the hardware
            device identified by the identity certificate.  If no
            Issuer enrollment has been performed, the AK certificate
            MAY be self-signed; verifiers SHOULD treat self-signed AK
            certificates as lower trust than Issuer-certified ones.
          </li>
          <li>
            <strong>Identity Certificate:</strong> Issued by the
            hardware manufacturer at fabrication time.  For TPMs, this
            is the EK certificate.  For PIV tokens, this is the device
            attestation certificate.  Contains the hardware identity
            public key, manufacturer identity, and device information.
            Signed by the manufacturer's intermediate CA.
          </li>
          <li>
            <strong>Manufacturer Intermediate CA Certificate(s):</strong>
            Zero or more intermediate CA certificates forming the chain
            between the identity certificate issuer and the
            manufacturer root.
          </li>
          <li>
            <strong>Manufacturer Root CA Certificate:</strong> The trust
            anchor.  This certificate SHOULD already be present in the
            verifier's trust store.  Major manufacturer root CAs are
            published at well-known URLs (e.g., Intel's Trusted
            Services API, AMD's Key Distribution Server, Yubico's
            attestation CA).
          </li>
        </ol>
      </section>

      <section anchor="header-format">
        <name>Header Field Definition</name>
        <t>
          This document defines the "Hardware-Attestation" header
          field for use in email messages.
        </t>

        <artwork type="abnf"><![CDATA[
Hardware-Attestation = "Hardware-Attestation" ":" SP hw-attest-value
                       CRLF

hw-attest-value = hw-version ";" SP
                  hw-type ";" SP
                  hw-algorithm ";" SP
                  hw-signed-hdrs ";" SP
                  hw-body-hash ";" SP
                  hw-timestamp ";" SP
                  hw-chain
                  [";" SP hw-aid]

hw-version     = "v" "=" "1"
hw-type        = "typ" "=" ("TPM" / "PIV" / "VRT" / "SFT")
hw-algorithm   = "alg" "=" ("RS256" / "ES256" / "PS256")
hw-signed-hdrs = "h" "=" hdr-name *(":" hdr-name)
hw-body-hash   = "bh" "=" base64url
hw-timestamp   = "ts" "=" 1*DIGIT
hw-chain       = "chain" "=" base64
hw-aid         = "aid" "=" aid-urn

hdr-name       = field-name  ; as defined in RFC 5322
base64url      = *( ALPHA / DIGIT / "-" / "_" )
                              ; URL-safe base64 per RFC 4648 Sec 5
base64         = *( ALPHA / DIGIT / "+" / "/" / "=" )
                              ; standard base64 per RFC 4648 Sec 4
        ]]></artwork>
        <t>
          The base64url and base64 encodings follow
          <xref target="RFC4648"/>.
        </t>

        <t>Where:</t>
        <dl>
          <dt>v</dt>
          <dd>Protocol version.  MUST be "1" for this specification.</dd>

          <dt>typ</dt>
          <dd>The hardware attestation mechanism type.  "TPM" for
          Trusted Platform Module (discrete or firmware), "PIV" for
          Personal Identity Verification smart card, "VRT" for virtual
          TPM, "SFT" for software-managed key.  Additional values MAY
          be registered with IANA.</dd>

          <dt>alg</dt>
          <dd>The signature algorithm used by the AK.  MUST be one of
          RS256 (RSASSA-PKCS1-v1_5 with SHA-256), ES256 (ECDSA with
          P-256 and SHA-256), or PS256 (RSASSA-PSS with SHA-256).
          RS256 is included for compatibility with existing TPM 2.0
          deployments where RSA keys are pre-provisioned; new
          deployments SHOULD prefer PS256 (for RSA) or ES256 (for
          ECC).  ES256 is RECOMMENDED for PIV tokens.  Additional
          algorithms MAY be registered with IANA (see
          <xref target="iana-considerations"/>); future versions of
          this specification MAY deprecate algorithms by updating
          the IANA registry.  Verifiers MUST reject algorithms not
          listed in the registry.  If SHA-256 is deprecated in the
          future, a new protocol version (v=2) would be required,
          as the hash algorithm is embedded in the attestation-digest
          construction.</dd>

          <dt>h</dt>
          <dd>A colon-separated list of header field names included in
          the h-hash computation, following the same conventions as
          the DKIM h= tag (<xref target="RFC6376"/> Section 3.5).
          The listed headers are canonicalised and concatenated (in
          the order listed) before hashing.  Signers MUST include at
          minimum: From, To, Subject, Date, and Message-ID.  Signers
          SHOULD also include any Hardware-Trust-Proof header present
          in the same message.  The Hardware-Attestation header itself
          is always implicitly appended last (with the chain
          parameter value replaced by the empty string during
          computation, following the same self-inclusion technique as
          DKIM-Signature per <xref target="RFC6376"/> Section 3.7).
          The Hardware-Attestation header MUST NOT appear in the h=
          list.  Because the header is included in h-hash, all of
          its parameters (including aid, typ, alg, bh, ts) are
          cryptographically bound to the signature.</dd>

          <dt>bh</dt>
          <dd>The base64url-encoded SHA-256 hash of the canonicalised
          email body, computed using the same canonicalisation algorithm
          as DKIM simple body canonicalisation
          <xref target="RFC6376" section="3.4.3"/>.</dd>

          <dt>ts</dt>
          <dd>Unix timestamp (seconds since 1970-01-01T00:00:00Z)
          at which the attestation signature was created.</dd>

          <dt>chain</dt>
          <dd><t>A base64-encoded CMS SignedData structure
          (<xref target="RFC5652"/>), using the SignedData content
          type (OID 1.2.840.113549.1.7.2).  The encapContentInfo
          MUST be absent (detached signature).  The chain parameter
          MUST be present; the full CMS structure is always inline
          in the header, ensuring that verifiers can perform
          cryptographic validation without any external fetches.
          The CMS structure contains: (a) the AK signature over
          the attestation digest (see below); (b) the AK
          certificate (Issuer-certified or self-signed); (c) the
          identity certificate (EK certificate for TPM, device
          attestation certificate for PIV); and (d) any
          intermediate CA certificates.</t>
          <t>The signed content is the SHA-256 hash of the
          concatenation of three fixed-length fields:</t>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
  attestation-input = h-hash || bh-raw || ts-bytes
  attestation-digest = SHA-256(attestation-input)
  signature = Sign(AK, attestation-digest)

  h-hash   = SHA-256(canonicalised-headers)  ; 32 bytes
  bh-raw   = SHA-256(canonicalised body)     ; 32 bytes
  ts-bytes = big-endian uint64(ts)           ; 8 bytes
          ]]></artwork>
          <t>The attestation-input is exactly 72 bytes (32 + 32 + 8).
          The canonicalised-headers input to h-hash is computed as
          follows: take the headers named in the h= parameter, in
          the order listed, each canonicalised per DKIM relaxed
          header canonicalisation (<xref target="RFC6376"/>
          Section 3.4.2) and terminated with CRLF.  Then append
          the Hardware-Attestation header itself, canonicalised
          the same way, with the chain parameter value replaced
          by the empty string, and without a trailing CRLF
          (matching the DKIM-Signature self-inclusion convention
          in <xref target="RFC6376"/> Section 3.7).  Because the
          Hardware-Attestation header contains the aid, typ, alg,
          bh, and ts parameters in their wire format, all of
          these values are cryptographically bound by h-hash.
          In particular, the aid parameter cannot be modified
          after signing without changing h-hash and therefore
          invalidating the signature.</t></dd>

          <dt>aid</dt>
          <dd>OPTIONAL.  The sender's agent identity URN as defined
          in <xref target="agent-identity-format"/>.  Because the
          Hardware-Attestation header is implicitly included in the
          canonicalised-headers input to h-hash (see the h and chain
          parameters above), the aid value is cryptographically
          bound to the signature.  Substitution or modification of
          the aid after signing invalidates the attestation.  The
          agent identity URN is the RECOMMENDED primary key for
          reputation tracking; verifiers SHOULD prefer aid over the
          hardware fingerprint when both are available, as the agent
          identity persists across hardware migrations (see
          <xref target="identity-hardware-cardinality"/>).  When aid
          is absent, the verifier can still validate the hardware
          certificate chain but has only the hardware fingerprint
          for reputation tracking.</dd>
        </dl>
      </section>

      <section anchor="verification-algorithm">
        <name>Verification Algorithm</name>
        <t>
          A receiving mail server that supports this specification
          MUST perform the following steps when a Hardware-Attestation
          header is present:
        </t>
        <ol>
          <li>
            Parse the Hardware-Attestation header field and extract v,
            typ, alg, h, bh, ts, chain, and (if present) aid.
            If parsing fails, the result is "none" (header malformed).
          </li>
          <li>
            Verify that v equals "1".  If not, the result is "none"
            (unsupported version).
          </li>
          <li>
            Verify that h lists at minimum From, To, Subject, Date,
            and Message-ID.  Compute h-hash as defined in
            <xref target="header-format"/>: canonicalise the listed
            headers using DKIM relaxed header canonicalisation
            (<xref target="RFC6376"/> Section 3.4.2), each
            terminated with CRLF, then append the
            Hardware-Attestation header itself (canonicalised the
            same way, with the chain value replaced by the empty
            string, without a trailing CRLF), and compute SHA-256
            over the result.
          </li>
          <li>
            Compute the SHA-256 hash of the canonicalised email body
            using DKIM simple body canonicalisation
            (<xref target="RFC6376"/> Section 3.4.3).  Base64url-decode
            the bh parameter value and compare the resulting octets
            with the computed hash (exact byte-for-byte comparison).
            If they differ, the result is "fail" (body modified).
          </li>
          <li>
            Verify that ts is within an acceptable window of the
            current time.  A window of 300 seconds (5 minutes) is
            RECOMMENDED for direct SMTP delivery.  Verifiers SHOULD
            allow a wider window (up to 3600 seconds / 1 hour) for
            messages that have passed through intermediate MTAs, as
            indicated by Received headers or queue delays.  If ts is
            outside the acceptable window, the result is "fail"
            (timestamp expired).
          </li>
          <li>
            Decode the base64 chain parameter to obtain the CMS
            SignedData structure.  Parse the CMS SignedData structure
            and extract the signer certificate (AK certificate) and
            the certificate chain.
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>Validate the certificate chain:</t>
            <ol type="a">
              <li>The AK certificate MUST contain evidence binding the
              AK public key to the identity certificate's device.
              For TPM-based attestation, this is a TPM2_Certify
              structure (either in an X.509 extension or as the
              certificate's subject public key attestation).  For
              PIV-based attestation, this is the manufacturer's
              attestation certificate chain (e.g., Yubico's
              attestation certificate that certifies the key was
              generated on the device).  For Issuer-certified AK
              certificates, the Issuer verified this binding during
              enrollment and the AK certificate is signed by the
              Issuer's CA.  For self-signed AK certificates, the
              verifier SHOULD treat the binding as unverified and
              reduce trust accordingly.</li>
              <li>The identity certificate MUST chain to a
              manufacturer intermediate CA certificate.</li>
              <li>The manufacturer intermediate CA MUST chain to a
              manufacturer root CA present in the verifier's
              hardware manufacturer CA trust store.</li>
            </ol>
            <t>If chain validation fails, the result is "fail"
            (chain invalid).</t>
          </li>
          <li>
            Reconstruct the attestation-digest as defined in
            <xref target="header-format"/>: concatenate h-hash
            (32 bytes), bh-raw (32 bytes, the raw SHA-256 digest
            of the canonicalised body), and ts-bytes (8 bytes,
            big-endian uint64 of ts), then compute SHA-256 over
            the 72-byte result.  Verify the CMS signature over
            this digest using the AK public key and the algorithm
            specified by alg.  If signature verification fails,
            the result is "fail" (bad signature).  Because the
            Hardware-Attestation header (including the aid
            parameter) is included in the canonicalised-headers
            input to h-hash, any modification to any header
            parameter after signing causes verification to fail.
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>If all checks pass, the result is "pass".  The verifier
            MAY extract the following information from the certificate
            chain and header:</t>
            <ul>
              <li>Hardware type (from typ parameter)</li>
              <li>Hardware manufacturer (from identity certificate
              issuer)</li>
              <li>Device model or family (from identity certificate
              extensions)</li>
              <li>Hardware fingerprint: SHA-256 hash of the identity
              certificate's public key</li>
              <li>Agent identity URN (from aid parameter, if
              present)</li>
            </ul>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>If aid is present, the verifier MAY additionally:</t>
            <ol type="a">
              <li>Discover the Issuer's endpoints per
              <xref target="issuer-discovery"/>.</li>
              <li>Query reputation services using the aid URN as
              a lookup key.</li>
              <li>Apply differentiated policy based on the agent's
              trust tier and reputation history.</li>
            </ol>
          </li>
        </ol>
      </section>

      <section anchor="auth-results">
        <name>Authentication-Results Integration</name>
        <t>
          When recording the result of Hardware-Attestation verification
          in an Authentication-Results header field
          <xref target="RFC8601"/>, the following method identifier and
          property types are used:
        </t>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
Authentication-Results: mx.example.com;
  hw-attest=pass
    header.typ=TPM
    header.alg=RS256
    header.mfr=INTC
    header.tier=sovereign
    header.fp=sha256:a1b2c3d4...
    header.aid=urn:aid:com.1id:1id-ty62muvf
        ]]></artwork>
        <t>Where:</t>
        <dl>
          <dt>hw-attest</dt>
          <dd>The method identifier.  Result is one of: "pass",
          "fail", "none" (header absent or unparseable), "temperror"
          (transient verification error), or "permerror" (permanent
          verification error).</dd>

          <dt>header.typ</dt>
          <dd>The hardware type from the Hardware-Attestation
          header.</dd>

          <dt>header.alg</dt>
          <dd>The signature algorithm.</dd>

          <dt>header.mfr</dt>
          <dd>The manufacturer code extracted from the identity
          certificate.  Common values: "INTC" (Intel), "AMD" (AMD),
          "IFX" (Infineon), "STM" (STMicroelectronics), "NTC"
          (Nuvoton), "YBK" (Yubico), "VMW" (VMware, virtual
          TPM).</dd>

          <dt>header.tier</dt>
          <dd>The inferred trust tier based on the hardware type and
          manufacturer.  Values: "sovereign", "portable", "virtual",
          "declared".</dd>

          <dt>header.fp</dt>
          <dd>The SHA-256 hash of the identity certificate's public
          key, truncated to the first 16 hex characters.  Serves as a
          compact hardware fingerprint for reputation tracking.  Full
          fingerprint SHOULD be available via an extended
          property.</dd>

          <dt>header.aid</dt>
          <dd>The agent identity URN from the aid parameter, if
          present.  Omitted if no aid was provided.</dd>
        </dl>
      </section>

      <section anchor="privacy-direct">
        <name>Privacy Considerations for Direct Attestation</name>
        <t>
          Direct Hardware Attestation reveals the sender's persistent
          hardware fingerprint to every recipient.  This linkability is
          a deliberate design choice for reputation systems; see
          <xref target="priv-fingerprint"/> for the full privacy
          analysis and <xref target="priv-mode2"/> for the
          privacy-preserving alternative.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <!-- ====================================================== -->
    <section anchor="sd-jwt-proof">
      <name>Mode 2: SD-JWT Trust Proof</name>

      <t>
        This section defines an SD-JWT-based trust proof using
        <xref target="RFC9901"/>.  Like the CMS bundle in Mode 1,
        the SD-JWT is transport-independent (see
        <xref target="design-principles"/>).
      </t>

      <section anchor="sd-jwt-overview">
        <name>Overview</name>
        <t>
          SD-JWT Trust Proof provides a privacy-preserving attestation
          mechanism where an Issuer (an entity that has previously
          verified the sender's hardware attestation) issues a
          per-message Selective Disclosure JWT
          <xref target="RFC9901"/> containing claims about the
          sender's trust classification and a cryptographic binding
          to the specific email being sent.  The claim structure is
          informed by the Entity Attestation Token (EAT) model
          <xref target="RFC9711"/>.
        </t>
        <t>
          For each outgoing email, the sending agent computes a
          message-binding hash (covering the email headers and body)
          and submits it to the Issuer over an authenticated channel.
          The Issuer verifies that the requesting agent is currently
          enrolled with valid hardware, creates an SD-JWT containing
          the message-binding hash as a nonce claim, and returns the
          signed token with disclosure values for all selectively
          disclosable claims.  The agent then selects which claims
          to reveal and includes the SD-JWT presentation in the
          email header.
        </t>
        <t>
          Because the Issuer signs the SD-JWT (not the agent), no
          agent-specific key appears in the token.  A recipient
          learns only what the sender chose to disclose -- for
          example, "my hardware trust tier is sovereign" -- without
          learning the sender's identity, hardware fingerprint, or
          any other persistent identifier.  The Issuer identifier
          (iss) and the message-binding nonce are always visible;
          all other claims are selectively disclosable.
        </t>
        <t>
          This mode requires the recipient to trust the Issuer's
          signing key (obtainable via DNS or the Issuer's JWKS
          endpoint per <xref target="issuer-discovery"/>).  It does
          NOT require trust in any hardware manufacturer CA, as the
          Issuer has already performed that verification during
          enrollment.
        </t>
        <t>
          The per-message Issuer interaction is the cost of full
          unlinkability: the agent must contact the Issuer for each
          email, and the Issuer becomes an availability dependency
          for Mode 2 senders.  If the Issuer is unreachable, the
          agent MAY fall back to Mode 1 (Direct Hardware Attestation)
          if its policy permits hardware fingerprint disclosure, or
          MAY defer sending until the Issuer recovers.  The Issuer
          learns that the agent is sending a message (and the timing
          thereof) but does not learn the message content -- only the
          message-binding hash, which is a SHA-256 digest from which
          content cannot be recovered.  Issuers MUST NOT log
          message-binding hashes or correlate them with message
          metadata beyond what is necessary for rate limiting and
          abuse prevention.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="sd-jwt-header">
        <name>Header Field Definition</name>
        <artwork type="abnf"><![CDATA[
Hardware-Trust-Proof = "Hardware-Trust-Proof" ":" SP
                       sd-jwt-presentation CRLF

sd-jwt-presentation = sd-jwt "~" *( disclosure "~" )

; sd-jwt and disclosure are defined in RFC 9901
        ]]></artwork>
        <t>
          The header value is an SD-JWT presentation as defined in
          <xref target="RFC9901"/>, consisting of the Issuer-signed
          JWT followed by zero or more disclosures.  No Key Binding
          JWT (KB-JWT) is included; message binding is provided by
          the nonce claim in the Issuer-signed payload (see
          <xref target="sd-jwt-message-binding"/>).
        </t>
        <t>
          The SD-JWT payload MUST include the following claims:
        </t>
        <dl>
          <dt>iss</dt>
          <dd>The Issuer's identifier (a URI matching the Issuer
          domain derived from the agent's URN namespace).  Used to
          locate the Issuer's signing key for signature
          verification.</dd>

          <dt>iat</dt>
          <dd>Issuance time as a NumericDate.  Because the SD-JWT
          is per-message, iat reflects the time the Issuer signed
          this specific token.</dd>

          <dt>exp</dt>
          <dd>Expiration time as a NumericDate.  MUST NOT exceed
          600 seconds (10 minutes) after iat.  This short validity
          window is appropriate because the SD-JWT is per-message:
          the agent requests a fresh token for each email, and the
          token need only remain valid long enough for the message
          to traverse the sending mail infrastructure.  Issuers
          SHOULD set exp to 300 seconds (5 minutes) after iat for
          typical deployments.</dd>

          <dt>nonce</dt>
          <dd>A base64url-encoded message-binding digest that
          cryptographically ties this SD-JWT to a specific email.
          Computed as defined in
          <xref target="sd-jwt-message-binding"/>.  This claim
          MUST be present and MUST NOT be selectively
          disclosable.</dd>

          <dt>_sd</dt>
          <dd>Array of digests for selectively disclosable claims,
          as defined in <xref target="RFC9901"/>.</dd>
        </dl>
        <t>
          The following claims SHOULD be available for selective
          disclosure (present as hashed entries in _sd):
        </t>
        <dl>
          <dt>trust_tier</dt>
          <dd>The sender's hardware trust classification.  Values
          include "sovereign" (genuine non-virtual hardware),
          "portable" (smart card / USB token), "virtual"
          (hypervisor-provided), and "declared" (software-only).</dd>

          <dt>sub</dt>
          <dd>The sender's agent identity URN as defined in
          <xref target="agent-identity-format"/>.</dd>

          <dt>handle</dt>
          <dd>A human-readable name for the sender, if assigned.</dd>

          <dt>hw_manufacturer</dt>
          <dd>The hardware manufacturer code (e.g., "INTC", "AMD",
          "YBK").</dd>

          <dt>enrolled_at</dt>
          <dd>The timestamp at which the sender enrolled with the
          Issuer.</dd>

          <dt>operator_email</dt>
          <dd>A contact address for the human operator responsible
          for this agent.  Allows relying parties to reach the
          accountable person without requiring the agent identity
          itself to be disclosed.</dd>

          <dt>hardware_locked</dt>
          <dd>Boolean indicating whether the identity is permanently
          bound to a single hardware device.  Once locked, the agent
          can no longer add or migrate to new devices.  This is an
          irreversible operation.</dd>

          <dt>locked_at</dt>
          <dd>Timestamp (ISO 8601) at which the hardware lock was
          applied.  Present only when hardware_locked is true.</dd>

          <dt>credential_pointer_count</dt>
          <dd>Integer count of registered credential pointers for
          this identity.  Allows a verifier to confirm that an agent
          has external credentials on file without revealing the
          credentials themselves.</dd>
        </dl>
      </section>

      <section anchor="sd-jwt-message-binding">
        <name>Message Binding via Issuer-Signed Nonce</name>
        <t>
          Each Mode 2 SD-JWT is per-message: the Issuer signs a
          fresh token for each email, incorporating a nonce claim
          that cryptographically binds the token to the specific
          message being sent.  Because the Issuer signs the token
          directly (rather than the agent signing a Key Binding JWT
          with a key embedded in the token), no agent-specific
          cryptographic material appears in the presentation.
        </t>
        <t>
          The message-binding nonce is computed by the sending agent
          before requesting the SD-JWT from the Issuer:
        </t>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
  message-binding = h-hash || bh-raw || ts-bytes
  nonce = base64url(SHA-256(message-binding))

  h-hash   = SHA-256(canonicalised-headers)  ; 32 bytes
  bh-raw   = SHA-256(canonicalised body)     ; 32 bytes
  ts-bytes = big-endian uint64(iat)          ; 8 bytes
        ]]></artwork>
        <t>
          The agent proposes an iat value (its current time) when
          requesting the token; the Issuer MUST reject proposed
          timestamps that differ from the Issuer's clock by more
          than 60 seconds.  The accepted iat becomes both the
          SD-JWT's iat claim and the timestamp used in ts-bytes,
          ensuring sender and verifier agree on the value.
        </t>
        <t>
          The canonicalised-headers are computed using the same
          rules as Mode 1 (see <xref target="header-format"/>):
          the headers From, To, Subject, Date, and Message-ID
          (at minimum) are canonicalised per DKIM relaxed header
          canonicalisation (<xref target="RFC6376"/> Section 3.4.2),
          each terminated with CRLF, then the
          Hardware-Trust-Proof header itself is appended last
          (canonicalised the same way, with its value replaced by
          the empty string, without a trailing CRLF).
        </t>
        <t>
          The agent submits the computed nonce and proposed iat to
          the Issuer over an authenticated channel (e.g., TLS
          client certificate authentication using the agent's
          hardware-resident key, or an OAuth2 token obtained during
          enrollment).  The Issuer verifies that the requesting
          agent is currently enrolled with valid hardware and has
          not been revoked, then creates and signs an SD-JWT
          containing the nonce along with selectively disclosable
          claims about the agent.  The Issuer returns the signed
          SD-JWT and the disclosure values for all selectively
          disclosable claims.  The agent selects which disclosures
          to include in the presentation.
        </t>
        <t>
          Because the nonce is embedded in the Issuer-signed
          payload, any modification to the email headers or body
          after the token is issued causes the nonce to mismatch
          during verification.  Because the Hardware-Trust-Proof
          header is included in the canonicalised-headers (with
          its value blanked during nonce computation), the choice
          of disclosed claims is also bound to the message.
        </t>
        <t>
          The Issuer's signature on the nonce serves a dual
          purpose: it proves that a currently enrolled agent with
          verified hardware requested this specific message
          binding, and it asserts the Issuer's claims about the
          agent's trust classification.  No agent-specific key
          appears in the token, so recipients cannot link multiple
          emails to the same sender based on the Mode 2 header
          alone.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="sd-jwt-verification">
        <name>Verification Algorithm</name>
        <ol>
          <li>
            Parse the Hardware-Trust-Proof header as an SD-JWT
            presentation per <xref target="RFC9901"/>.  The
            presentation consists of the Issuer-signed JWT and
            zero or more disclosures; no Key Binding JWT is
            expected.
          </li>
          <li>
            Extract the issuer (iss) claim from the SD-JWT payload.
          </li>
          <li>
            Obtain the Issuer's public key.  The verifier MUST
            first check for a DNS-published key (see
            <xref target="issuer-key-dns"/>).  If no DNS record
            is found, the verifier MAY fall back to the Issuer's
            HTTPS JWKS endpoint
            (e.g., {iss}/.well-known/jwks.json).  Cached keys
            SHOULD have a TTL of at least 1 hour and at most
            24 hours.
          </li>
          <li>
            Verify the SD-JWT signature against the Issuer's public
            key per <xref target="RFC9901"/>.
          </li>
          <li>
            Verify that exp has not passed and iat is within an
            acceptable window.  Because Mode 2 SD-JWTs are
            per-message, the RECOMMENDED exp is 300 seconds after
            iat; verifiers SHOULD reject tokens where exp exceeds
            iat by more than 3600 seconds (1 hour).
          </li>
          <li>
            For each disclosure present, verify that its hash matches
            an entry in the _sd array.
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>Verify the message binding.  Extract the nonce claim
            from the SD-JWT payload.  If absent, the result is
            "fail" (missing message binding).  Recompute the
            expected message-binding digest as defined in
            <xref target="sd-jwt-message-binding"/>: canonicalise
            the email headers (From, To, Subject, Date, Message-ID
            at minimum) and body, compute message-binding =
            h-hash || bh-raw || ts-bytes (using the SD-JWT's iat
            for ts-bytes), then
            base64url(SHA-256(message-binding)).  Compare the
            result with the nonce claim value.  If they differ,
            the result is "fail" (message binding mismatch).</t>
          </li>
          <li>
            Extract the disclosed claims.  The result is "pass"
            with the set of verified claims.
          </li>
        </ol>
      </section>

      <section anchor="sd-jwt-auth-results">
        <name>Authentication-Results Integration</name>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
Authentication-Results: mx.example.com;
  hw-trust=pass
    header.trust_tier=sovereign
    header.registry=1id.com
        ]]></artwork>
        <dl>
          <dt>hw-trust</dt>
          <dd>The method identifier.  Result values are the same as
          for hw-attest.</dd>

          <dt>header.trust_tier</dt>
          <dd>The disclosed trust tier value, if the sender chose to
          reveal it.</dd>

          <dt>header.registry</dt>
          <dd>The Issuer domain (derived from the iss claim).</dd>
        </dl>
      </section>
    </section>

    <!-- ====================================================== -->
    <section anchor="combined-mode">
      <name>Combined Mode</name>
      <t>
        A sending agent MAY include both Hardware-Attestation and
        Hardware-Trust-Proof headers in the same message.  When both
        are present:
      </t>
      <ul>
        <li>
          Receivers that trust hardware manufacturer CAs but not the
          Issuer SHOULD verify Hardware-Attestation and ignore
          Hardware-Trust-Proof.
        </li>
        <li>
          Receivers that trust the Issuer but prefer not to process
          the full certificate chain SHOULD verify
          Hardware-Trust-Proof and MAY ignore Hardware-Attestation.
        </li>
        <li>
          Receivers that support both SHOULD verify both and record
          both results in Authentication-Results.  Agreement between
          the two mechanisms provides defence-in-depth: compromising
          either the manufacturer CA or the Issuer alone is
          insufficient to forge both attestations.
        </li>
      </ul>
      <t>
        The two mechanisms are independent.  Failure of one MUST NOT
        cause the other to be treated as failed.
      </t>
    </section>

    <!-- ====================================================== -->
    <section anchor="sybil-resistance">
      <name>Sybil Resistance Properties</name>
      <t>
        The primary security goal of this specification is Sybil
        resistance: making it economically infeasible for an attacker
        to create many sender identities.
      </t>
      <section anchor="sybil-mode1">
        <name>Direct Hardware Attestation (Mode 1)</name>
        <t>
          Each hardware security component contains exactly one identity
          key, which produces exactly one identity certificate.  The
          hardware fingerprint (identity certificate public key hash)
          provides the underlying Sybil resistance: creating N
          identities requires N physical devices.
        </t>
        <t>
          The agent identity URN (aid) is the RECOMMENDED primary key
          for reputation tracking.  When aid is present, verifiers
          SHOULD build reputation against the aid rather than the
          hardware fingerprint, because the aid persists across
          hardware migrations (see
          <xref target="identity-hardware-cardinality"/>).  The
          hardware fingerprint serves as a secondary signal that
          anchors the identity to physical hardware and enables
          reputation tracking for agents that do not present an aid.
        </t>
        <t>
          A receiving mail server that tracks agent identities (or,
          when aid is absent, hardware fingerprints) can enforce
          policies such as:
        </t>
        <ul>
          <li>Rate limiting per agent identity</li>
          <li>Reputation scoring per agent identity</li>
          <li>Blocking agent identities associated with abuse</li>
        </ul>
        <t>
          An attacker attempting to evade these policies requires a
          new physical hardware security component (minimum cost: the
          device itself at ~$20 plus potentially a host machine at
          ~$200-2000), compared to zero cost for creating a new
          software identity.
        </t>
        <t>
          Multiple agents sharing the same hardware (e.g., multiple
          VMs on a server with a single TPM) share the same hardware
          fingerprint and therefore linked reputations.  This shared
          fate model creates economic incentive for infrastructure
          operators to police their tenants: if one agent on a machine
          misbehaves, all agents on that machine inherit the
          reputational consequences.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sybil-mode2">
        <name>SD-JWT Trust Proof (Mode 2)</name>
        <t>
          Sybil resistance in Mode 2 depends on the Issuer's
          enrollment policy.  An Issuer that assigns trust_tier values
          indicating hardware verification (e.g., "sovereign") MUST
          verify hardware attestation at enrollment time and MUST
          enforce the cardinality constraints defined in
          <xref target="identity-hardware-cardinality"/>: at most one
          agent identity per hardware device within that Issuer's
          namespace, while permitting hardware migration (multiple
          devices backing the same identity over time).  Such an
          Issuer provides equivalent Sybil resistance to Mode 1,
          with the additional benefit that the hardware fingerprint
          is not revealed to email recipients.
        </t>
        <t>
          Issuers SHOULD monitor for anomalous enrollment patterns
          (e.g., many enrollments from a single IP range or a sudden
          spike in enrollments from a specific manufacturer CA) and
          SHOULD be capable of suspending enrollments pending
          investigation.
        </t>
        <t>
          An Issuer that enrolls software-only agents (trust_tier
          "declared") provides no hardware-based Sybil resistance and
          MUST NOT assign trust_tier values that imply hardware
          verification.  The trust_tier claim distinguishes these
          cases, enabling recipients to weight trust appropriately.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sybil-vtpm">
        <name>Virtual Hardware</name>
        <t>
          Virtual TPMs (vTPMs) provided by hypervisors (VMware,
          Hyper-V, QEMU) have valid identity certificates signed by
          the hypervisor vendor's CA, but the hypervisor operator can
          instantiate arbitrary numbers of vTPMs.  Virtual TPMs
          therefore provide no hardware-based Sybil resistance against
          the hypervisor operator.  They do, however, provide benefits
          over software-only keys (typ=SFT):
        </t>
        <ul>
          <li>Key persistence managed by the hypervisor (the agent
          does not need to store key material).</li>
          <li>Modest cost barriers (provisioning a vTPM is slower and
          more resource-intensive than generating a software key
          pair).</li>
          <li>Reputation accumulation incentive (discarding a vTPM
          identity forfeits its accumulated reputation).</li>
        </ul>
        <t>
          Receiving mail servers MUST distinguish between physical and
          virtual hardware.  The identity certificate's issuer field
          identifies the manufacturer: VMware-issued or Microsoft
          Hyper-V-issued certificates indicate a virtual TPM.  The
          header.tier property in Authentication-Results ("sovereign"
          vs "virtual") and the typ parameter ("TPM" vs "VRT")
          communicate this distinction.
        </t>
        <t>
          Mail servers SHOULD apply significantly different reputation
          thresholds for virtual vs. physical hardware.  For
          high-trust scenarios, verifiers MAY reject virtual TPM
          attestation entirely and require physical hardware (typ=TPM
          or typ=PIV).
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <!-- ====================================================== -->
    <section anchor="interaction-dkim">
      <name>Interaction with Existing Email Authentication</name>
      <t>
        The mechanisms defined in this document complement rather
        than replace existing email authentication:
      </t>
      <dl>
        <dt>SPF <xref target="RFC7208"/></dt>
        <dd>Verifies the sending IP is authorised for the domain.
        Orthogonal to hardware attestation.  Both SHOULD be used.</dd>

        <dt>DKIM <xref target="RFC6376"/></dt>
        <dd>Provides domain-level signing.  Hardware-Attestation
        provides device-level signing.  They protect different
        properties: DKIM proves domain authorisation;
        Hardware-Attestation proves hardware identity.
        Both SHOULD be used.</dd>

        <dt>DMARC <xref target="RFC7489"/></dt>
        <dd>Ties SPF and DKIM together with policy.  A future
        extension to DMARC could incorporate hardware attestation
        results into the policy evaluation.  This is out of scope
        for this document.</dd>

        <dt>ARC <xref target="RFC8617"/></dt>
        <dd>Preserves authentication results through forwarding
        chains.  ARC SHOULD preserve Hardware-Attestation and
        Hardware-Trust-Proof Authentication-Results when forwarding
        messages.</dd>

        <dt>S/MIME <xref target="RFC8551"/></dt>
        <dd>Provides end-to-end encryption and sender signing via
        CA-issued certificates.  S/MIME and Hardware-Attestation
        operate at different layers and coexist without interference:
        S/MIME wraps or signs the message body within MIME structures,
        while Hardware-Attestation adds a header field alongside the
        message.  The body hash (bh) in the Hardware-Attestation
        header is computed over the raw canonicalised body, including
        any S/MIME MIME structures.  A message MAY carry both S/MIME
        signatures and hardware attestation simultaneously.</dd>

        <dt>OpenPGP / PGP/MIME <xref target="RFC3156"/></dt>
        <dd>Like S/MIME, OpenPGP operates at the body level
        (encrypting or signing the message content within MIME
        structures).  Hardware-Attestation operates at the header
        level.  The two mechanisms are fully orthogonal: a PGP-signed
        message can carry a Hardware-Attestation header, and the
        verifier processes each independently.</dd>
      </dl>

      <section anchor="multiple-headers">
        <name>Multiple Headers and Forwarding</name>
        <t>
          If multiple Hardware-Attestation headers are present in a
          message (e.g., if a forwarding gateway adds its own
          attestation), the verifier SHOULD evaluate all of them
          independently and record each result separately in
          Authentication-Results, using the same precedence
          conventions as for multiple DKIM-Signature headers
          <xref target="RFC6376"/>.
        </t>
        <t>
          Mailing lists and content-modifying forwarders that alter
          the message body will invalidate the body hash (bh) in
          any existing Hardware-Attestation header.  This is expected
          and analogous to DKIM signature breakage through body
          modification.  Such intermediaries SHOULD preserve the
          original Hardware-Attestation header (the verifier will
          record "fail" due to body hash mismatch) and MAY add their
          own Hardware-Attestation header covering the modified body,
          if the intermediary itself has hardware attestation
          capability.  ARC <xref target="RFC8617"/> SHOULD be used to
          preserve the original authentication results from before
          the modification.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <!-- ====================================================== -->
    <section anchor="submission-requirements">
      <name>Message Submission Requirements</name>

      <t>
        The attestation signature in the Hardware-Attestation header is
        produced by the sending agent, not by the mail server.  When
        the aid parameter is present, it is cryptographically bound to
        the signature (see <xref target="header-format"/>), so any
        modification of the aid after signing causes verification to
        fail at the receiving end.  As defence-in-depth, Mail
        Submission Agents (MSAs) that accept messages from
        hardware-attested senders MUST also enforce identity binding
        at submission time, rejecting messages before they enter the
        mail system rather than relying solely on receiver-side
        verification.
      </t>
      <t>
        Agents submitting messages through an attestation-aware MSA
        MUST authenticate to the MSA.  The MSA SHOULD support
        authentication using the agent's hardware-resident key
        (e.g., TLS client certificate authentication where the
        client certificate is signed by the same AK used for
        attestation, or a challenge-response protocol using the
        TPM or PIV signing key).  This ensures that the MSA can
        verify the submitting agent controls the hardware
        corresponding to the attestation header, preventing
        credential-theft scenarios where SMTP credentials are
        compromised but the hardware is not.
      </t>

      <section anchor="submission-aid-binding">
        <name>Agent Identity Binding at Submission</name>
        <t>
          When an MSA receives a message containing a
          Hardware-Attestation header with an aid (agent identity)
          parameter, the MSA MUST verify that the aid value
          corresponds to the authenticated account submitting the
          message.  The binding between authenticated account and
          permitted agent identity URN(s) is established during
          account provisioning and is outside the scope of this
          specification, but the enforcement is normative:
        </t>
        <ul>
          <li>
            If the aid value does not match any agent identity URN
            authorised for the submitting account, the MSA MUST reject
            the message with an appropriate error (e.g., SMTP 550
            "5.7.1 Agent identity not authorised for this account").
          </li>
          <li>
            If the Hardware-Attestation header is present but contains
            no aid parameter, the MSA SHOULD still verify that the
            hardware fingerprint (derived from the chain parameter)
            corresponds to hardware registered to the
            submitting account, if such a registry is available.
          </li>
          <li>
            If the MSA does not implement hardware attestation
            verification, it MUST NOT strip or modify the
            Hardware-Attestation header.  The header will be evaluated
            by downstream verifiers.
          </li>
        </ul>
        <t>
          This requirement parallels the existing SMTP AUTH obligation:
          just as an MSA enforces that the envelope sender (MAIL FROM)
          and header From address belong to the authenticated user, an
          attestation-aware MSA enforces that the agent identity
          belongs to the authenticated agent.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="submission-hw-fingerprint-binding">
        <name>Hardware Fingerprint Binding at Submission</name>
        <t>
          For Mode 1 (Direct Hardware Attestation), the MSA SHOULD
          extract the hardware fingerprint from the attestation chain
          and verify it against the fingerprint registered to the
          submitting account.  This prevents an attacker who has
          obtained valid SMTP credentials from substituting a
          different device's attestation evidence.
        </t>
        <t>
          For Mode 2 (SD-JWT Trust Proof), the MSA SHOULD verify that
          the Issuer (iss claim) and, if disclosed, the agent identity
          URN (sub claim) are consistent with the submitting account's
          registered identity.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="submission-no-attestation">
        <name>Messages Without Attestation</name>
        <t>
          An MSA that serves hardware-attested agents MAY also accept
          messages without Hardware-Attestation or Hardware-Trust-Proof
          headers, subject to its own policy.  The absence of
          attestation headers from a known-attested account SHOULD be
          logged as anomalous but MUST NOT cause message rejection
          unless the account's policy explicitly requires attestation
          on every message.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="submission-duplicate-headers">
        <name>Duplicate Header Rejection</name>
        <t>
          An MSA MUST reject any submitted message that contains more
          than one Hardware-Attestation header field.  A legitimate
          sender produces exactly one attestation per message.
          Multiple Hardware-Attestation headers in a submitted
          (non-forwarded) message indicate either a software defect
          or an injection attempt.  This check MUST occur before
          DKIM signing, so that the MSA never signs a message
          containing duplicate attestation headers.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="submission-timestamp-validation">
        <name>Timestamp Validation at Submission</name>
        <t>
          The MSA SHOULD verify that the ts value in the
          Hardware-Attestation header is within a reasonable window
          of the current time (RECOMMENDED: 60 seconds).  A
          timestamp significantly in the past may indicate a replayed
          header; a timestamp in the future may indicate clock
          manipulation intended to extend the attestation's apparent
          validity.  If the timestamp is outside the acceptable
          window, the MSA SHOULD reject the message.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <!-- ====================================================== -->
    <section anchor="interoperability">
      <name>Interoperability Considerations</name>

      <section anchor="backward-compat">
        <name>Backward Compatibility</name>
        <t>
          This specification introduces new email headers that are
          ignored by mail servers that do not implement it.  Messages
          carrying Hardware-Attestation or Hardware-Trust-Proof headers
          are fully compatible with legacy mail infrastructure: the
          headers are simply unrecognised and have no effect on
          delivery.  This ensures that deployment can proceed
          incrementally without disrupting existing email flows.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="signing-order">
        <name>DKIM Coverage of Attestation Headers</name>
        <t>
          Because the sending agent adds the Hardware-Attestation
          and Hardware-Trust-Proof headers before submitting the
          message to the MSA, DKIM signing (which occurs at the
          MSA or a downstream MTA) naturally occurs after these
          headers are present.  The DKIM signer SHOULD include
          Hardware-Attestation and Hardware-Trust-Proof in the
          DKIM-Signature h= tag so that the DKIM signature
          protects the attestation evidence against modification
          in transit.  This allows a verifier to confirm that the
          domain owner's mail infrastructure accepted the
          attestation header as submitted by the agent.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="header-size">
        <name>Header Size Considerations</name>
        <t>
          The base64-encoded CMS chain in Mode 1 can be several
          kilobytes, depending on the number of intermediate CA
          certificates.  Implementations SHOULD use line folding per
          <xref target="RFC5322"/> to keep individual header lines
          within the 998-octet limit.  Mail servers that impose
          maximum header size limits SHOULD allow at least 8192 octets
          for the Hardware-Attestation header value.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <!-- ====================================================== -->
    <section anchor="implementation-status">
      <name>Implementation Status</name>
      <t>
        NOTE TO RFC EDITOR: Please remove this section before
        publication.
      </t>
      <t>
        This section records the status of known implementations of
        the protocol defined by this specification at the time of
        posting of this Internet-Draft, and is based on a proposal
        described in <xref target="RFC7942"/>.
      </t>

      <section>
        <name>1id.com Issuer</name>
        <t>
          Organisation: 1id.com (https://1id.com)
        </t>
        <t>
          Description: An implementation of Mode 2 (SD-JWT Trust
          Proof) as described in this draft, with Mode 1 (Direct
          Hardware Attestation) in development.  The implementation
          includes server-side identity certificate chain validation
          against manufacturer root CAs (Intel, AMD, Infineon,
          STMicroelectronics, Nuvoton, Qualcomm, Yubico), anti-Sybil
          enforcement via a one-device-per-identity registry, and
          SD-JWT trust proof issuance with selective disclosure of
          nine claims (sub, handle, trust_tier, hw_manufacturer,
          enrolled_at, operator_email, hardware_locked, locked_at,
          credential_pointer_count).  The system supports both
          TPM-based and PIV-based (YubiKey) attestation, including
          co-location binding ceremonies.  Agent identities use the
          <tt>urn:aid:com.1id:</tt> namespace.
        </t>
        <t>
          Maturity: Beta.  Deployed in production at https://1id.com.
        </t>
        <t>
          Coverage: Mode 2 (SD-JWT Trust Proof) is fully implemented,
          including transient-only AK model for TPM attestation with
          no NV storage writes, multi-device identity management with
          hardware lock, and per-message SD-JWT issuance.  Mode 1
          (Direct Hardware Attestation via CMS) is in development.
        </t>
        <t>
          Contact: Christopher Drake &lt;cnd@1id.com&gt;
        </t>
        <t>
          Open-source components:
        </t>
        <ul>
          <li>
            <strong>Python SDK:</strong>
            <eref target="https://github.com/1id-com/oneid-sdk"/> --
            Client-side enrollment and attestation library.  Published
            to PyPI as "oneid".
          </li>
          <li>
            <strong>Node.js SDK:</strong>
            <eref target="https://github.com/1id-com/oneid-node"/> --
            Client-side enrollment and attestation library.  Published
            to npm as "1id".
          </li>
          <li>
            <strong>Hardware helper binary:</strong>
            <eref target="https://github.com/1id-com/oneid-enroll"/> --
            Cross-platform Go binary for TPM access (Windows TBS, Linux
            /dev/tpmrm0), PIV smart card operations, and AK
            provisioning.
          </li>
          <li>
            <strong>Internet-Draft companion repository:</strong>
            <eref target="https://github.com/1id-com/draft-drake-email-hardware-attestation"/> --
            Draft XML source, example verification code for both modes,
            and test vectors.
          </li>
          <li>
            <strong>Manufacturer CA Trust Store:</strong>
            <eref target="https://github.com/1id-com/tpm-manufacturer-cas"/> --
            Community-curated collection of hardware manufacturer root
            CA certificates for identity certificate chain validation,
            as referenced in
            <xref target="appendix-manufacturer-cas"/>.
          </li>
        </ul>
      </section>

      <section>
        <name>MailPal.com Verifier and Relay</name>
        <t>
          Organisation: Crypt Inc. (https://mailpal.com)
        </t>
        <t>
          Description: An email service (Stalwart Mail Server on
          Linux) intended to implement end-to-end hardware attestation
          for both sending and receiving.  Planned capabilities
          include: on the outbound path, MSA validation of
          Hardware-Attestation and Hardware-Trust-Proof headers at
          submission time per
          <xref target="submission-requirements"/>, agent identity
          binding enforcement, and attestation header inclusion in
          DKIM signature coverage.  On the inbound path, verification
          of both Mode 1 certificate chains and Mode 2 SD-JWT trust
          proofs, Authentication-Results recording per
          <xref target="auth-results"/> and
          <xref target="sd-jwt-auth-results"/>, and
          trust-tier-differentiated delivery policy.
        </t>
        <t>
          Maturity: Alpha.  Mail infrastructure deployed at
          https://mailpal.com; attestation header verification in
          development.
        </t>
        <t>
          Coverage: Mail transport infrastructure is operational.
          Attestation header generation, submission validation, and
          inbound verification are in development.
        </t>
        <t>
          Contact: Christopher Drake &lt;cnd@1id.com&gt;
        </t>
        <t>
          Open-source components:
        </t>
        <ul>
          <li>
            <strong>Attestation verification library:</strong>
            <eref target="https://github.com/1id-com/hw-attest-verify"/> --
            Verification of Mode 1 CMS attestation bundles and
            Mode 2 SD-JWT trust proofs.  Suitable for integration
            into any MTA or mail filter.
          </li>
        </ul>
      </section>
    </section>

    <!-- ====================================================== -->
    <section anchor="iana-considerations">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>

      <section>
        <name>Header Field Registration</name>
        <t>
          IANA is requested to register the following header fields
          in the "Permanent Message Header Field Names" registry:
        </t>
        <dl>
          <dt>Hardware-Attestation</dt>
          <dd>Applicable protocol: mail.  Status: standard.
          Reference: this document,
          <xref target="header-format"/>.</dd>

          <dt>Hardware-Trust-Proof</dt>
          <dd>Applicable protocol: mail.  Status: standard.
          Reference: this document,
          <xref target="sd-jwt-header"/>.</dd>
        </dl>
      </section>

      <section>
        <name>Authentication Method Registration</name>
        <t>
          IANA is requested to register the following entries in the
          "Email Authentication Methods" registry
          <xref target="RFC8601"/>:
        </t>
        <dl>
          <dt>hw-attest</dt>
          <dd>Definition: this document,
          <xref target="auth-results"/>.
          Applicable versions: 1.</dd>

          <dt>hw-trust</dt>
          <dd>Definition: this document,
          <xref target="sd-jwt-auth-results"/>.
          Applicable versions: 1.</dd>
        </dl>
      </section>

      <section>
        <name>Hardware Attestation Type Registry</name>
        <t>
          IANA is requested to create a new registry titled "Hardware
          Attestation Type Values" with the following initial entries.
          New entries require Specification Required
          (<xref target="RFC8126"/>).
        </t>
        <table>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Value</th>
              <th>Description</th>
              <th>Reference</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td>TPM</td>
              <td>TPM 2.0 (discrete or firmware)</td>
              <td>this document</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>PIV</td>
              <td>PIV smart card / USB token</td>
              <td>this document</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>VRT</td>
              <td>Virtual TPM (hypervisor-provided)</td>
              <td>this document</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>SFT</td>
              <td>Software-managed key</td>
              <td>this document</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </section>

      <section>
        <name>URN Namespace Registration</name>
        <t>
          IANA is requested to register the "aid" URN namespace
          identifier in the "Formal URN Namespaces" registry per
          <xref target="RFC8141"/>.  The registration template is
          provided in <xref target="urn-registration"/>.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <!-- ====================================================== -->
    <section anchor="security-considerations">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>

      <section anchor="manufacturer-ca-compromise">
        <name>Manufacturer CA Compromise</name>
        <t>
          If a hardware manufacturer's root CA private key is
          compromised, an attacker could forge identity certificates and
          create unlimited fake hardware identities.  This risk is
          inherent to any PKI-based system and is mitigated by the same
          measures that protect manufacturer CAs today: hardware
          security modules, air-gapped signing ceremonies, and
          Certificate Transparency <xref target="RFC9162"/>.
        </t>
        <t>
          The SD-JWT Trust Proof (Mode 2) provides partial mitigation:
          if the Issuer detects anomalous enrollment patterns (e.g.,
          thousands of enrollments from a single manufacturer CA in a
          short period), it can suspend enrollments while the compromise
          is investigated.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="revocation-and-compromise">
        <name>Revocation and Compromise Response</name>
        <t>
          This specification does not define a real-time certificate
          revocation protocol.  Compromise of individual hardware
          devices or keys is handled at multiple layers:
        </t>
        <dl>
          <dt>Compromised or stolen device (TPM, YubiKey)</dt>
          <dd>The device owner notifies their Issuer, which revokes
          the agent identity.  The Issuer publishes revocation status
          via its JWKS or a revocation endpoint; verifiers that cache
          Issuer metadata will detect the revocation at the next
          refresh.  For Mode 1, the hardware fingerprint SHOULD be
          added to a local blocklist.  The device's reputation history
          (which now includes the abuse) persists and follows the
          hardware fingerprint even if re-enrolled under a new
          identity.</dd>

          <dt>Manufacturer CA breach</dt>
          <dd>Verifiers MUST remove the compromised CA from their
          trust store.  The IANA Hardware Attestation Type registry
          (see <xref target="iana-considerations"/>) and the
          community-maintained manufacturer CA trust store (see
          <xref target="appendix-manufacturer-cas"/>) provide
          distribution channels for updated trust anchors.</dd>

          <dt>Rogue Issuer</dt>
          <dd>Verifiers remove the Issuer from their allowlist.
          Because Issuer trust is a local policy decision (see
          <xref target="issuer-trust"/>), no central revocation
          mechanism is required: each verifier independently decides
          which Issuers to trust, analogous to browser root store
          management for TLS CAs.</dd>
        </dl>
        <t>
          The absence of a real-time revocation check (such as OCSP)
          is a deliberate trade-off: adding a synchronous revocation
          check to the email delivery path would introduce latency
          and a new availability dependency.  The short validity
          window for SD-JWT trust proofs (600 seconds) and the
          per-message timestamp in Mode 1 limit the exposure window
          for compromised credentials.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="replay-attacks">
        <name>Replay Attacks</name>
        <t>
          The timestamp (ts) in the Hardware-Attestation header limits
          the replay window.  Receiving mail servers SHOULD reject
          attestations with timestamps more than 300 seconds from the
          current time for direct SMTP delivery, and up to 3600 seconds
          for messages with evidence of intermediate relay hops.
          Additionally, the body hash (bh) binds the attestation to a
          specific email body, preventing a valid attestation from being
          attached to a different message.
        </t>
        <t>
          For SD-JWT Trust Proofs, each SD-JWT is per-message: the
          nonce claim in the Issuer-signed payload binds the token
          to the specific email's headers and body, and the short
          validity window (RECOMMENDED 300 seconds) limits the
          replay window.  An attacker who intercepts a valid SD-JWT
          cannot reuse it for a different message because the nonce
          will not match.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="compromised-endpoints">
        <name>Compromised Endpoints</name>
        <t>
          This specification does not prevent a compromised device from
          sending attested email -- if an attacker has full control of a
          device with hardware security, they can use that hardware to
          attest.  However, this is by design: each compromised device
          contributes exactly one hardware identity, and that identity
          accrues reputation (good or bad) permanently.  A botnet of
          10,000 compromised devices yields 10,000 attestable
          identities, not the millions possible with software-only
          identity systems.
        </t>
        <t>
          The transient key model (<xref target="transient-key-model"/>)
          reduces the privilege requirements for per-message signing.
          Initial enrollment (the one-time MakeCredential /
          ActivateCredential exchange) typically requires elevated
          operating system privileges (administrator on Windows via the
          TPM Base Services API, or root on Linux via /dev/tpmrm0).
          Subsequent signing operations (TPM2_Sign with the transient
          AK) MAY be available to unprivileged processes depending on
          the operating system configuration.  On Windows, a one-time
          registry configuration can grant non-administrator processes
          access to TPM signing operations.
        </t>
        <t>
          The net effect is that hardware attestation raises the bar for
          email abuse from "any script" to "compromise of a specific
          physical device," which is a substantial improvement over the
          status quo even if it is not a complete solution.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="hardware-attacks">
        <name>Physical Attacks on Hardware Security Components</name>
        <t>
          Extracting private keys from a TPM or PIV token requires
          physical attacks such as electron microscopy, laser fault
          injection, or side-channel analysis.  Modern security
          components include countermeasures against these attacks.  The
          cost and expertise required for successful key extraction is
          estimated at $50,000-$200,000 per chip, making it economically
          unviable for spam operations.
        </t>
        <t>
          Even if key extraction were feasible, the extracted key could
          only impersonate one hardware identity.  The attacker would
          still need to extract keys from additional devices to create
          additional identities.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="virtual-tpm-risk">
        <name>Virtual Hardware Risk</name>
        <t>
          Virtual TPMs do not provide the same Sybil resistance as
          physical hardware; see <xref target="sybil-vtpm"/> for
          the detailed analysis and policy guidance.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="software-only-risk">
        <name>Software-Only Attestation Risk</name>
        <t>
          Software-managed keys (typ=SFT) provide no hardware-based
          Sybil resistance; an attacker can generate unlimited key
          pairs at zero cost.  Verifiers MUST treat software-only
          attestation (trust_tier "declared") as fundamentally weaker
          than hardware-backed attestation.  Software-only attestation
          exists to enable inclusive participation, not to provide
          Sybil resistance (see <xref target="design-principles"/>).
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="transient-object-limits">
        <name>Transient Object Slot Limits</name>
        <t>
          TPMs have a limited number of transient object slots (typically
          3 to 7 simultaneously loaded objects).  If all slots are
          occupied, TPM2_CreatePrimary returns TPM_RC_OBJECT_MEMORY
          (0x0902).  Implementations MUST handle this error by flushing
          unused transient handles (TPM2_FlushContext) and retrying.
          Failure to flush transient objects can cause denial of service
          to other TPM-using applications on the same device.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="policy-abuse">
        <name>Policy Abuse and Deanonymisation Risk</name>
        <t>
          This specification targets AI agents, bots, and autonomous
          systems (see <xref target="applicability"/>).  It is not
          intended for individual human senders and is not expected
          to be incorporated into Mail User Agents (MUAs) designed
          for interactive human use.  The privacy trade-offs inherent
          in hardware attestation -- particularly the persistent
          hardware fingerprint exposed by Mode 1 -- are acceptable
          for automated senders whose identity is operationally
          transparent, but disproportionate for human
          correspondence.
        </t>
        <t>
          However, an AI agent may compose and send email on behalf
          of an individual (e.g., an executive assistant agent
          sending calendar invitations, or a customer service agent
          responding to support tickets).  In such delegated-sending
          scenarios, the attestation identifies the agent and its
          hardware, not the human principal.  Operators deploying
          agents that send on behalf of individuals SHOULD be aware
          that the persistent hardware fingerprint (Mode 1) or the
          Issuer identifier (Mode 2) may allow recipients to
          correlate messages across different human principals
          served by the same agent.  Where this correlation is
          undesirable, operators SHOULD use Mode 2 without
          disclosing the agent identity URN, or SHOULD deploy
          separate agent identities per human principal.
        </t>
        <t>
          The persistent hardware fingerprint exposed by Mode 1 (see
          <xref target="priv-fingerprint"/> for linkability details)
          creates specific abuse scenarios even in automated
          contexts:
        </t>
        <ul>
          <li>Authoritarian regimes could correlate hardware
          fingerprints across messages to identify the
          organisations operating specific agents.</li>
          <li>Platforms could mandate Mode 1 attestation to
          deanonymise agents that have legitimate reasons for
          pseudonymity (e.g., whistleblower-support bots,
          journalist-source-protection agents).</li>
          <li>Receiving mail servers that log hardware fingerprints
          create long-lived tracking databases linking agent
          activity across recipients and time periods.</li>
        </ul>
        <t>
          Mode 2 (SD-JWT Trust Proof) mitigates these risks by
          eliminating persistent agent-specific identifiers from the
          token; see <xref target="priv-mode2"/>.  Receiving mail
          servers SHOULD NOT require Mode 1 attestation when Mode 2
          provides sufficient trust signal for the receiver's policy
          needs.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="header-stripping">
        <name>Header Stripping and Modification</name>
        <t>
          An intermediary mail server could strip or modify the
          Hardware-Attestation or Hardware-Trust-Proof headers.  This
          risk is identical to the risk of DKIM signature stripping and
          is mitigated by the same mechanisms: ARC
          <xref target="RFC8617"/> preserves authentication results
          through forwarding chains.
        </t>
        <t>
          Stripping these headers cannot cause a legitimate message to
          appear illegitimate (it simply loses the attestation).  Adding
          forged headers is prevented by the cryptographic signatures.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="credential-theft-and-replay">
        <name>Credential Theft and Identity Substitution</name>
        <t>
          Because the attestation signature is produced by the sending
          agent rather than by the mail server, theft of SMTP
          credentials alone does not grant the attacker a valid
          attestation.  The agent identity (aid), when present, is
          cryptographically bound to the signature: substituting a
          different aid value causes signature verification to fail
          at the receiving end.
        </t>
        <t>
          An attacker who intercepts a legitimately signed attestation
          header could attempt to replay it on a different message.
          The body hash (bh), timestamp (ts), and signed header hashes
          (h-hash) prevent replay on altered content.  The MSA
          identity binding requirements in
          <xref target="submission-requirements"/> provide
          defence-in-depth: an attestation-aware MSA rejects messages
          where the agent identity does not match the submitting
          account, preventing misuse before the message enters the
          mail system.
        </t>
        <t>
          Together, the cryptographic binding of aid in the signature
          and the MSA submission-time enforcement ensure that an
          agent cannot claim an identity other than its own.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="issuer-trust">
        <name>Issuer Trust and Accountability</name>
        <t>
          The federated issuance model
          (<xref target="issuer-discovery"/>) means verifiers MUST
          make their own trust decisions about which Issuers to accept.
          A malicious Issuer could issue multiple identities for the
          same hardware, undermining Sybil resistance.  However, this
          violation is detectable: verifiers that track hardware
          fingerprints will observe the same fingerprint appearing
          under multiple agent identities from the same Issuer,
          which constitutes direct evidence of Issuer misbehaviour.
        </t>
        <t>
          Verifiers SHOULD maintain an allowlist of trusted Issuers,
          analogous to browser trust stores for TLS CAs.  Reputation
          services MAY track Issuer quality metrics (enrollment
          anomaly rates, duplicate-fingerprint detections, abuse
          report correlations) to inform verifier trust decisions.
          Verifiers SHOULD remove Issuers from their allowlist when
          evidence of policy violations is detected.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <!-- ====================================================== -->
    <section anchor="privacy-considerations">
      <name>Privacy Considerations</name>

      <t>
        This section consolidates the privacy implications of this
        specification, per <xref target="RFC6973"/>.  Hardware
        attestation inherently involves persistent identifiers; the
        privacy properties differ significantly between the two modes
        and between automated and human senders.
      </t>

      <section anchor="priv-scope">
        <name>Applicability to Human vs. Automated Senders</name>
        <t>
          This specification targets authentication of automated
          senders -- AI agents, bots, and high-volume automated
          systems.  It is NOT intended or recommended for individual
          human users sending personal or low-volume email.  The
          persistent hardware fingerprint in Mode 1 uniquely identifies
          the sending device across all messages and contexts, creating
          linkability that exceeds current email privacy norms for
          human correspondence.
        </t>
        <t>
          Operators of human-facing email services that offer hardware
          attestation as an opt-in feature MUST provide clear disclosure
          of the linkability implications before activation.  Receivers
          SHOULD NOT penalise the absence of hardware attestation from
          senders exhibiting human-characteristic patterns.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="priv-fingerprint">
        <name>Hardware Fingerprint Linkability</name>
        <t>
          Mode 1 (Direct Hardware Attestation) exposes a persistent,
          globally unique hardware fingerprint -- the SHA-256 hash of
          the identity certificate's public key -- to every recipient.
          This fingerprint is stable for the lifetime of the hardware
          device and is identical across all protocols (email, HTTP,
          agent-to-agent) where the same device attests.
        </t>
        <t>
          Any party that observes this fingerprint can correlate
          messages across recipients, time periods, and transport
          protocols.  This cross-context linkability is the intended
          mechanism for reputation building in automated sender
          scenarios, but it also enables surveillance if misused.
        </t>
        <t>
          The identity certificate additionally reveals the hardware
          manufacturer and device model family.  In most automated
          deployments this information is not sensitive, but it does
          narrow the set of possible senders.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="priv-mode2">
        <name>Privacy-Preserving Alternative (Mode 2)</name>
        <t>
          Mode 2 (SD-JWT Trust Proof) provides Sybil resistance
          without revealing the hardware fingerprint or any
          persistent agent-specific identifier.  Because the Issuer
          signs the per-message SD-JWT directly (rather than the
          agent signing with a key embedded in the token), no
          agent-controlled key appears in the presentation.
          Recipients cannot link multiple emails to the same sender
          based on Mode 2 headers alone.
        </t>
        <t>
          The sender selects which claims to disclose; the hardware
          fingerprint, agent identity URN, and device details can
          all be withheld.  Only the Issuer identifier (iss) and
          the message-binding nonce are always visible.
        </t>
        <t>
          The privacy cost of full unlinkability is that the agent
          must contact the Issuer for each email, so the Issuer
          learns the agent's sending pattern (timing and frequency)
          though not the message content.  Issuers MUST NOT log or
          correlate message-binding hashes beyond what is necessary
          for rate limiting and abuse prevention (see
          <xref target="priv-issuer"/>).
        </t>
        <t>
          Senders operating in contexts where hardware fingerprint
          disclosure is unacceptable -- including agents that wish
          to avoid cross-context tracking -- SHOULD use Mode 2
          exclusively.  Receivers SHOULD NOT require Mode 1 when
          Mode 2 provides sufficient trust signal for their policy
          needs.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="priv-issuer">
        <name>Issuer Knowledge</name>
        <t>
          During enrollment, the Issuer learns the agent's hardware
          fingerprint (identity certificate public key hash) and
          associates it with the assigned agent identity URN.  This
          is necessary for anti-Sybil enforcement.
        </t>
        <t>
          In Mode 2, the Issuer additionally learns that the agent
          is sending a message each time the agent requests a
          per-message SD-JWT.  The Issuer receives the
          message-binding hash (a SHA-256 digest from which message
          content cannot be recovered) but does not learn the
          message recipients, subject, or body.  Issuers MUST NOT
          log message-binding hashes or correlate per-message
          signing requests with external data to infer message
          content or recipients.  Issuers SHOULD implement rate
          limiting at the per-message signing endpoint to prevent
          abuse, but MUST delete signing request metadata
          (timestamps, source IPs, message-binding hashes) within
          24 hours.
        </t>
        <t>
          The specification deliberately separates enrollment
          (Issuer) from behaviour tracking (reputation services)
          to limit the Issuer's knowledge of agent activity.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="priv-data-minimisation">
        <name>Data Minimisation</name>
        <t>
          Verifiers that record hardware fingerprints or agent identity
          URNs for reputation purposes SHOULD apply data minimisation
          principles: retain only the truncated fingerprint (as
          specified in <xref target="auth-results"/>) rather than the
          full identity certificate, and SHOULD define retention
          policies that limit how long fingerprint-to-message
          associations are stored.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>

    <references>
      <name>Normative References</name>

      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>

      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4648.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5652.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6376.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8141.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8601.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9901.xml"/>

    </references>

    <references>
      <name>Informative References</name>

      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1035.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3156.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5322.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5891.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7208.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7489.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7671.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7942.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8126.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8551.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8617.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6973.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9162.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9334.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9711.xml"/>

      <reference anchor="TCG-TPM2"
                 target="https://trustedcomputinggroup.org/resource/tpm-library-specification/">
        <front>
          <title>TPM 2.0 Library Specification</title>
          <author>
            <organization>Trusted Computing Group</organization>
          </author>
          <date year="2024" month="December"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="TCG" value="Revision 185"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="TCG-EK-PROFILE"
                 target="https://trustedcomputinggroup.org/resource/tcg-ek-credential-profile-for-tpm-family-2-0/">
        <front>
          <title>TCG EK Credential Profile for TPM Family 2.0</title>
          <author>
            <organization>Trusted Computing Group</organization>
          </author>
          <date year="2024" month="December"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="TCG" value="Version 2.6"/>
      </reference>

    </references>

    <!-- ====================================================== -->
    <section anchor="appendix-economics">
      <name>Appendix: Economics of Hardware-Based Sybil Resistance</name>
      <t>
        The following table compares the cost of creating N fake
        sender identities under various authentication regimes:
      </t>
      <table>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th>Authentication</th>
            <th>Cost per Identity</th>
            <th>Cost of 1M Identities</th>
            <th>Reusable After Flag?</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td>Email-only</td>
            <td>~$0</td>
            <td>~$0</td>
            <td>Yes (new address)</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Phone-verified</td>
            <td>~$0.01-0.10</td>
            <td>$10K-100K</td>
            <td>Yes (new SIM)</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Domain + DKIM</td>
            <td>~$1-10</td>
            <td>$1M-10M</td>
            <td>Yes (new domain)</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Hardware Attestation</td>
            <td>~$20-2000</td>
            <td>$20M-2B</td>
            <td>No (device is permanent)</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
      <t>
        The critical difference is the "Reusable After Flag?" column.
        With every existing mechanism, a flagged identity can be cheaply
        replaced.  With hardware attestation, a flagged hardware
        identity is permanently associated with that physical device.
        The attacker must procure entirely new hardware.
      </t>
    </section>

    <!-- ====================================================== -->
    <section anchor="appendix-manufacturer-cas">
      <name>Appendix: Hardware Manufacturer Root CAs</name>
      <t>
        The following hardware manufacturers publish root CA
        certificates that can be used to validate identity certificate
        chains:
      </t>
      <dl>
        <dt>Intel</dt>
        <dd>Provides EK CA certificates via a REST API for firmware
        TPM (Platform Trust Technology / PTT) and discrete TPM
        devices.  See
        <eref target="https://trustedservices.intel.com/"/>.</dd>

        <dt>AMD</dt>
        <dd>AMD Security Processor key distribution for fTPM EK
        validation.  See
        <eref target="https://download.amd.com/sev/"/>.</dd>

        <dt>Infineon</dt>
        <dd>Infineon OPTIGA TPM certificates.  Root CA available via
        Infineon's PKI.  See
        <eref target="https://www.infineon.com/TPM"/>.</dd>

        <dt>STMicroelectronics</dt>
        <dd>Root certificates available through ST's TPM documentation
        portal.</dd>

        <dt>Nuvoton</dt>
        <dd>Root certificates available through Nuvoton's security
        products documentation.</dd>

        <dt>Yubico</dt>
        <dd>PIV attestation CA certificates for YubiKey devices.
        See
        <eref target="https://developers.yubico.com/PIV/Introduction/piv-attestation.html"/>.</dd>
      </dl>
      <t>
        Receiving mail servers implementing this specification SHOULD
        maintain a local trust store of hardware manufacturer root CAs,
        updated periodically.  A community-maintained trust store
        (analogous to Mozilla's CA certificate programme for TLS) would
        benefit the ecosystem.  An open-source trust store project is
        available at
        <eref target="https://github.com/1id-com/tpm-manufacturer-cas"/>.
      </t>
    </section>

    <!-- ====================================================== -->
    <section anchor="other-transports">
      <name>Appendix: Applicability to Other Transports</name>
      <t>
        The CMS attestation bundle (the "chain" value defined in
        <xref target="header-format"/>) and the SD-JWT trust proof
        (defined in <xref target="sd-jwt-header"/>) are self-contained
        data structures whose verification algorithms
        (<xref target="verification-algorithm"/> and
        <xref target="sd-jwt-verification"/>) do not depend on email
        semantics.  The body hash (bh) generalises to a content hash
        over whatever payload the attestation covers.
      </t>
      <t>
        Potential transport bindings include but are not limited to:
      </t>
      <dl>
        <dt>HTTP</dt>
        <dd>The CMS attestation bundle or SD-JWT trust proof could be
        carried in HTTP request headers or in HTTP message bodies.
        The content hash would cover the HTTP request or response
        payload.  This binding is particularly relevant for API calls
        by autonomous AI agents, where the receiving service benefits
        from verifying that the request originated on attested
        hardware.  The agent identity URN
        (<xref target="agent-identity-format"/>) provides a persistent
        key for cross-protocol reputation tracking.</dd>

        <dt>Agent-to-Agent Protocols</dt>
        <dd>Emerging protocols for AI agent communication -- tool
        invocation, task delegation, capability discovery -- could
        carry attestation evidence alongside each request, enabling
        agents to verify each other's hardware trust level before
        exchanging sensitive data or delegating privileged
        operations.</dd>

        <dt>WebSocket and Streaming Protocols</dt>
        <dd>Attestation evidence could be presented during connection
        establishment (e.g., in the WebSocket upgrade request) to
        establish hardware trust for the duration of a persistent
        connection.</dd>
      </dl>
      <t>
        Detailed specification of these bindings is out of scope for
        this document and is deferred to future companion documents.
      </t>
    </section>

    <!-- ====================================================== -->
    <section anchor="urn-registration">
      <name>Appendix: URN Namespace Registration for "aid"</name>
      <t>
        This appendix provides the registration template for the "aid"
        (Agent Identity) URN namespace, per
        <xref target="RFC8141"/> Section 5.1.
      </t>
      <dl>
        <dt>Namespace Identifier</dt>
        <dd>aid</dd>

        <dt>Version</dt>
        <dd>1</dd>

        <dt>Date</dt>
        <dd>2026-02-28</dd>

        <dt>Registrant</dt>
        <dd>
          <t>Crypt Inc. (Delaware C-Corp, operational since 2006)</t>
          <t>Contact: Christopher Drake &lt;cnd@1id.com&gt;</t>
          <t>URI: https://1id.com</t>
          <t>The registrant is committed to long-term stewardship of
          this namespace.  As the ecosystem of Issuers and verifiers
          grows, the registrant intends to establish a multi-stakeholder
          governance body to oversee namespace policy.  Interested
          parties are invited to participate via the companion
          repository at
          https://github.com/1id-com/draft-drake-email-hardware-attestation.</t>
        </dd>

        <dt>Purpose</dt>
        <dd>
          <t>
            The "aid" URN namespace provides persistent, globally
            unique identifiers for autonomous agents, designed
            specifically to enable reputation systems and Sybil-resistant
            authentication across Internet protocols.
          </t>
          <t>
            As AI agents become ubiquitous across email, APIs, and
            Internet services, platforms need stable identifiers that:
            (1) distinguish legitimate agents from malicious ones,
            (2) accumulate reputation over time,
            (3) are anchored to unique physical hardware where available,
            and (4) support federated issuance by multiple independent
            identity providers.
          </t>
          <t>
            URNs in this namespace are bound to hardware security
            components (TPM chips, PIV tokens, virtual TPMs) or to
            software-managed keys at a lower trust tier.  The namespace
            supports multiple issuers, each identified by a reverse-DNS
            issuer-namespace within the URN structure.
          </t>
        </dd>

        <dt>Syntax</dt>
        <dd>
          <t>See <xref target="agent-identity-format"/> for the
          formal ABNF.  The general form is:</t>
          <t><tt>urn:aid:{issuer-namespace}:{agent-id}</tt></t>
          <t>where {issuer-namespace} is a reverse-DNS domain
          (e.g., "com.1id") and {agent-id} is a DNS-label-syntax
          identifier assigned by the Issuer (e.g.,
          "1id-ty62muvf").</t>
        </dd>

        <dt>Assignment</dt>
        <dd>
          <t>
            Agent identifiers are assigned by Issuers -- organisations
            that operate enrollment services, verify hardware
            attestation, and maintain anti-Sybil registries.  Any
            organisation owning a DNS domain can operate as an Issuer.
            Issuer-namespace uniqueness is guaranteed by DNS ownership.
            Agent-id uniqueness within a namespace is guaranteed by the
            Issuer's assignment policy.  An Issuer MUST NOT reassign an
            agent-id, even after revocation.
          </t>
        </dd>

        <dt>Security and Privacy</dt>
        <dd>
          <t>
            See the Security Considerations
            (<xref target="security-considerations"/>) of this
            document.  Agent identity URNs are persistent and globally
            unique by design, enabling long-term reputation tracking.
            For privacy-sensitive contexts, SD-JWT selective disclosure
            (<xref target="sd-jwt-proof"/>) allows agents to prove
            trust properties without revealing their URN.
          </t>
        </dd>

        <dt>Interoperability</dt>
        <dd>
          <t>
            URNs in this namespace appear in: JWT sub claims (OpenID
            Connect tokens), email headers (Hardware-Attestation,
            Hardware-Trust-Proof), HTTP Authorization headers, and
            reputation service APIs.  Standard URN parsers
            (<xref target="RFC8141"/>) and standard JWT libraries
            process these identifiers without modification.
          </t>
        </dd>

        <dt>Resolution</dt>
        <dd>
          <t>
            Resolution is OPTIONAL.  Issuers MAY provide resolution
            services returning public identity metadata.  The resolution
            URL is derived by reversing the issuer-namespace to obtain
            the Issuer domain and appending a well-known path.
            Resolution, when available, returns trust tier, registration
            timestamp, and optional handle -- but never authentication
            history or private data.
          </t>
        </dd>

        <dt>Documentation</dt>
        <dd>This document
        (draft-drake-email-hardware-attestation-00).</dd>

        <dt>Revision Information</dt>
        <dd>Initial registration.</dd>
      </dl>
    </section>

    <!-- ====================================================== -->
    <section anchor="acknowledgements">
      <name>Acknowledgements</name>
      <t>
        The concept of using hardware attestation for email sender
        verification was developed in the context of building a
        hardware identity registrar for autonomous AI agents.  The
        author thanks the Trusted Computing Group for the TPM 2.0
        specification, the authors of <xref target="RFC9901"/> (SD-JWT)
        for the selective disclosure mechanism, the authors of
        <xref target="RFC9334"/> (RATS Architecture) for establishing
        the remote attestation architecture that this document builds
        upon, and the authors of <xref target="RFC8141"/> (URN) for the
        persistent identifier framework that underpins the federated
        agent identity model.
      </t>
    </section>

  </back>

</rfc>